<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certayne reasons and arguments proving that it is not lawfull to heare or have any spirituall communion with the present ministerie of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Francis, 1562-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 239 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103950</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839692</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68281)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 558:13, 802:5, 1270:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certayne reasons and arguments proving that it is not lawfull to heare or have any spirituall communion with the present ministerie of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Francis, 1562-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 112, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Thorpe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yeare of our Lord: 1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of P2, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 10401.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10401 on UMI microfilm reel 1270, and as STC 14660a on UMI microfilm reels 558 and 802.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library, the Bodleian Library, and the Library of Congress.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 558 đ (Folger Shakespeare Library copy, identified as STC 14660a), reel 802 #5 (Bodleian Library copy, identified as STC 14660a), and at reel 1270, ⁸ (Library of Congress copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAYNE REASONS and Arguments Proving that it is not lawfull to heare or have any ſpirituall communion with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church of England.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ier. 50.14.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Put your ſelves in aray againſt Babel round about, all that bend the bow, ſhoot at her, ſpare not arrowes: for ſhe hath ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against the Lord.</p>
               <p>Cry againſt her round about, ſhe hath given her hand, her foundations be fallen, her walles be deſtroyed: becauſe it is the vengeance of the Lord, take vengeance vpon her: as ſhe hath done, do vnto her.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 18.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Reward her even as ſhe hath rewarded you, and double vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her doubles according to her workes: in the cup wherein ſhe hath mixed, mixe her the double.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, In the yeare of our Lord: 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader, grace and peace in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Reaſons following, I have publiſhed (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) for thy good, and for the truthes ſake which we wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the world. The cauſes of our ſeparation from the Church of England are divers, as in other Books already printed may be ſeen. This treatiſe handleth purpoſely but one of them, which is concerning their preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie: and was (for the ſubſtance of it) written long ſynce in nine Reaſons, which now I have reviſed and reduced to ſeven. In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding and handling whereof, I have both inſerted divers things which I met with in ſome writings of Mr <hi>Iohn Penry</hi> that faithfull Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr of Ieſus Chriſt; and annexed ſundry teſtimonies and Arguments out of the Books of the forward Preachers now abroad in mens hands. The third Reaſon, which is taken out of <hi>Rev. 14.9.10.11.</hi> hath his weight according to the right vnderſtanding of that place. Concerning which (as <hi>Mr Ridley</hi> that bleſſed Martyr of Chriſt<note n="†" place="margin">See here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, p. 59.</note> did in his time) I will commit the judgement thereof, and of all the reſt, <hi>to the ſpirituall man:</hi> to be tryed and judged by the word of God, which is the onely rule of truth; and ſo to be received and approved, as they ſhalbe found to beare weight, being layd in the ſkoales of Gods ſanctuary; &amp; not any otherwiſe or further at all.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons are ſet downe in the forme of Syllogiſmes. And the two firſt (which conteyne in them the grounds of the reſt) have more ſpecially the confirmation of them alſo handled after the ſame manner. A courſe that ſome have deſired for the further tryall of our cauſe. Which now I wiſh it may help them forward to yeeld vnto the truth. And if thy ſelf (Chriſtian Reader) reapeſt any fruit by our labours, give God praiſe, and pray for vs the vnworthieſt of his ſervants, who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where contemned blaſphemed and oppugned, for the Name of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Ier. 30.17. Mat. 5.12. and 10.25. Heb. 12.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. &amp;c.</note> As hath ben the lot of the Churches and ſervants of God in all ages, yea and of Chriſt our Lord himſelf. But <hi>it is ynough for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to be as his Maiſter, and the ſervant as his Lord.</hi> Therefore will we beare it with pacience, and rejoyce in it: wayting till the Lord our God bring forth his truth as the light, &amp; our judgement as the noone day. Great (we know) is the truth, and ſtrong is the Lord, that will deſtroy Babylon, and will mainteyne the cauſe and avenge the blood of his ſervants. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>and 18. and 19. chap. with Ier. 50. and 51. ch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore let me exhort all, both Preachers and people, high and low, to compare together the Scriptures of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles concerning the work of God and fall of Babylon paſt and to come; and to take heed vnto themſelves, that they harden not their hearts, but whiles it is called To day, to hearken vnto the voice of the Lord, who ſayth vnto vs concerning the ſpirituall Babylon &amp; all her aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies
<pb facs="tcp:4135:3"/>
and worſhip, <hi>Go out of her my people, that yee partake not with her ſinnes, and that ye receive not of her plagues:</hi> as of old he ſayd to the Iewes concerning Babylon in Chaldea, <hi>Go out of the middes of her my people, &amp; deliver ye every man his ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fierce wrath of the Lord. Rev. 18.4. with Ier. 51.45.</hi> And let there be heard,<note n="*" place="margin">Ier. 50.28. with Rev. 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the voyce of them that flee and eſcape out of the land of Babel, to declare in Zion the vengeance of the Lord our God, the vengeance of his Temple.</hi> For it is written, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, The thick walles of Babel ſhalbe broken downe, and her high gates ſhalbe burnt with fire; and the people ſhall labour in vayne, and the folk in the fire, and ſhalbe weary. Ier. 51.58.</hi> Which how true it is &amp; wilbe found in the Antichriſtian Babylon, as it hath ben in the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, let all that are wiſe obſerve, &amp; make good vſe thereof vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>And in ſpeciall (as now I have occaſion) let me intreat the Preachers ſeeking reformation, ſeriouſly to mynd the Books which many of them ſelves have written againſt their preſent eſtate, &amp; with indifferency to judge whether their owne Arguments (howſoever intended or alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged otherwiſe by themſelves) rely not vpon ſuch grounds, as are in very deed againſt their Miniſtery, aſwell as againſt their Ceremonies; againſt the executing of the one, aſwel as againſt the vſing of the other; &amp; withall againſt the keeping of communion with them in ſuch eſtate: albeit they have not hitherto ſo applyed or acknowledged it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves. Which God in his tyme give them to do for their owne comfort &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of others.</p>
            <p>And the Lord guyde vs in theſe and all other things by his word and ſpirit in the way of his truth, keeping vs from errour and every evill way, and preſerving vs to his heavenly kingdome, by Ieſus Chriſt: who is the way, the truth, and the life. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thyne in the Lord: <hi>Francis Iohnſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:3"/>
            <head>REASONS and proofes from the Scriptures, and other teſtimonies, Shewing that it is not lawful to heare or have any ſpiritual communion with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</head>
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <head>The firſt Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll are bound in the worship of God to hear and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate onely with that Miniſterie which Chriſt hath given, and ſet in his Church, for that work.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of England is not that which Chriſt hath given, and ſet in his Church, for the work of his Miniſtery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therfore it is not lawful for any in the worship of God to hear or communicate with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyes of England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The proof and declaration of this Reaſon, in the ſeveral parts thereof.</p>
               <p>THe Propoſition or firſt part of the Reaſon is evident and certayn: 1. Becauſe Chriſt hath given his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie to his Church, as a fruit and confirmation of his aſcenſion into heaven, whoſe gift therfore cannot therin be refuſed without denying or derogating from the truth and benefit of that his aſcenſion. <hi>Ephe. 4.8,</hi>—12. <hi>with Pſ. 68.18.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13.16.17.18.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe he hath ſet his Miniſterie in his Church, as Lord and King therof, whoſe appointment therefore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4135:4"/>
may not be altered or diſobeyed. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.5.28. <hi>with Heb. 3.</hi>5.<hi>6. &amp;</hi> 9.10.11. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.46. <hi>and</hi> 19.27. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.13.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe he buildeth and worketh by and in his owne Miniſterie, as God, who is gracious and powerful, working all in all, to whom therfore in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip all ſubmiſſion and obedience is to be yeelded in his own Miniſterie onely, and in no other whatſoever. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6.28. <hi>with Heb.</hi> 3.3.4. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1,—15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8.16.20. <hi>and</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.1.14.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe to his owne Miniſterie onely, he calleth his people and promiſeth his preſence and bleſſing: ſo as in rejecting it &amp; admitting another, men do (as much as in them lyeth) reject and refuſe his bleſſed preſence, and deny the obedience which they ow vnto him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.3.4.5.13.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. <hi>and</hi> 3.1. <hi>with Lev.</hi> 26.11.12.15.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.10.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.6.7.8. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.20.21. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.10.15.16.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19.20.</p>
               <p>THe Aſſumption or latter part of the Reaſon, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thus:</p>
               <p>The Miniſterie which Chriſt hath given and ſet in his Church, is of Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors, and Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
               <p>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church of England is none of thoſe, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
               <p>Therfore it is not the Miniſterie which Chriſt hath given and ſet in his Church.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition is playn and vndenyable. The Aſſumption is ſhewed thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4135:4"/>The preſent Miniſtery of the Church of Engl. is of Prelates, Prieſts, and Deacons:</p>
               <p>But neyther the Prelates, Prieſts, nor Deacons of that Church be Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors or Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
               <p>Therfore the preſent Miniſtery of that Church is none of thoſe, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition is manifeſt by their Law, &amp; conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The <hi>Law</hi> of that Church eſtabliſheth not nor admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any other Miniſtery, but that of their <hi>Prelacy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Deaconry,</hi> received among themſelves or from the Papiſts. Their <hi>conſtitution</hi> is ſuch, as al the Miniſters of that Church muſt be <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Deacons.</hi> And theſe alſo eyther in a ſuperiour degree, as <hi>the Prelates,</hi> the Lordbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Archbs, Suffraganes, &amp;c. or in an inferiour, as the Parſons, Vicars, Stipendaries, Chapleynes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption is thus proved:</p>
               <p>And firſt concerning the three firſt ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>The offices of the Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts, were extraordinary &amp; the chiefeſt appointed by chriſt, for ſpecial imployme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in laying the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> church &amp; religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through the world, preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel every where, erecting the kingdom of God in al nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, opening &amp; foretelling the things revealed vnto them by the holy Ghoſt, planting the Primitive Churches, and ſetling them in the faith and ordinance of Ieſus Chriſt which ſhould continue to the end of the world, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But ſuch are not the offices of the Prelates, Prieſts, or Deacons of the Church of England.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4135:5"/>Therfore they are not the Apoſtles, Prophets, or Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>More particularly:</p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. were ſuch, as every one of them had &amp; were to have theſe properties, That with their eyes they had ſeen the L. Ieſus, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1. <hi>and</hi> 15.7.8.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.39.40.41. That by him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they were appointed to that office, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2.24 25.26. <hi>with Prov.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. That of him (and not of man) they received the doctrine and commandements which they delivered to the Churches, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That they were ſent into the whole world to preach the Goſpel to everie creature, to the Iewes and Gentiles of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.20. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.15. <hi>and</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 14 <hi>chap. &amp;c.</hi> That as Maiſter-builders they layd the foundation which ſhould alway continue to the end, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19.20. <hi>with</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10.11. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.11.12.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14. That they ſhould all be of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall authority, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25.26.27. 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 12.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14. That they were filled with the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, with variety of tongues, ability to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, power to work miracles, and to ſhew vndoubted argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of their Apoſtleſhip, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; 5. ch. &amp;c. with Ioh.</hi> 16.13 <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.21.22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11.12.</p>
               <p>But ſuch are not the Prelates Prieſts or Deacons in the Church of England.</p>
               <p>Therfore they are not the Apoſtles, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. And Paul ſayth, that God ſet forth him and Barnabas the laſt Apoſtles, appointed to death, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9. If they were the laſt, how ſhal we now look for any mo after them? Or if any wil yet ſo think of themſelves or others, we may be ſure the tryall of them by the word of God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4135:5"/>
wil evince them to be ſuch as the Church of Epheſus fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be lyars, which ſaid they were <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but were not to in deed. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. were ſuch as (with the Apoſtles) had the Goſpel revealed vnto them by the Spirit, and delivered it for the foundation of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches and religion, and by ſpeciall revelation o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened &amp; applyed the Scriptures of the former Prophets, and in waighty caſes foretold things to come, as by the holy Ghoſt was ſhewed vnto them. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>and</hi> 2.20. <hi>with 4.</hi>11.<hi>12. 1 Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.28. <hi>and</hi> 21.10.11.</p>
               <p>But ſuch are not the Prelates Prieſts or Deacons of the Church of England.</p>
               <p>Therfore they are not the Prophets, ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. were ſuch as having appointment &amp; direction by the Spirit or the Apoſtles, preached the Goſpel abroad, and brought the Churches to a ſetled eſtate, according to the order preſcribed them by the Apoſtles, whoſe companions and aſſiſtants they were, going whither they ſent them, and returning whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would have them. <hi>Act.</hi> 21.8. <hi>with chap.</hi> 8.5.12.26 29.30.35.39.40. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.9.10.11. <hi>with Rom.</hi> 16.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>and</hi> 16.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1.19. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.19.22. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>&amp;c. and with Act.</hi> 16.1.3, <hi>and</hi> 17.14.15. <hi>and</hi> 18.5. <hi>and</hi> 19.22. <hi>and</hi> 20.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.10.11. <hi>with Act.</hi> 15.39.40. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.4.5. <hi>and</hi> 3.12. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23.</p>
               <p>But ſuch are not the Prelates Prieſts or Deacons of the Church of England.</p>
               <p>Therfore they are not the Evangeliſts, ſpoken of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>The Propoſitions of theſe particular reaſons are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4135:6"/>
by the ſcriptures annexed vnto them.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumptions are ſo playne as they need no proof at all. And if any would deny them, they ar bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſhew the contrary by the Scriptures: Which none can ever do.</p>
               <p>Now as the Prelates Prieſts &amp; Deacons of the church of England are not Apoſtles, Prophets, or Evangeliſts, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. ſo neyther are they Paſtors or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers there ſpoken of by the Apoſtle. Which now we wil alſo prove.</p>
               <p>But firſt (for further clearing of the truth and better diſcerning of their eſtate) it is to be obſerved here, that albeit themſelves take it for granted that they have theſe offices in their Church, yet they neyther have agreed nor can agree among themſelves who they be that have them; whether the prelates, or the other prieſts, &amp;c. but are at a great jarre and in deed at a playne contradiction among themſelves hereabout. Many of the Prelates and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſts ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Bridges, Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>that their Archbishops and Bishops are Paſtors &amp; Teachers;</hi> Some of them ſay,<note n="‖" place="margin">Whitgift a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt T.C. p. 137. Andr. in the 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. with M. Barrow.</note> 
                  <hi>that a Bishop is ſuperior both in office and gifts to a Pastor.</hi> Many of the Reformiſts ſay, that <note n="‡" place="margin">Mr. Sperin; M. Egerton, in the Confer. M. Hilderſ. M. Iacob, in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</note>
                  <hi>the learned and painful Parſons of Parishes and Lecturing prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers among them are Paſtors and Teachers;</hi> Others of them ſay,<note n="†" place="margin">Mr. Chader<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in the Sermon on Rom. 12. p. 33. &amp;c. Admon to the Parliam. 1. &amp; 2.</note> 
                  <hi>they want Paſtors and Teachers and all the offices appointed by Chriſt to his Church;</hi> that <hi>the Prelates robbe the Church of of lawful Paſtors Elders and Deacons;</hi> that their <hi>Parſons, Vicars, Parish Prieſts, Stipendaries, and the reſt, came from the Pope as out of the Troiane horſes belly to the deſtruction of Gods kingdome;</hi> that <hi>they are the Prelates new creatures;</hi> and that <hi>the Church of God never knew them.</hi> And all the ſeekers of Reformation have ſhewed to the Parliament heretofore, that <hi>the names and offices of Archbishops, Archdeacons, Lordbishops, and the reſt,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4135:6"/>
are together with their government drawen out of the Popes shop, and contrary to the Scriptures;</hi> that <hi>the Parſons, Vicars, Parish— prieſts, and Stipendaries, be birds of the ſame fether;</hi> and that <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey have an Antichriſtian hierarchie and popish ordering of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſtrange from the word of God and the vſe of all well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in the world.</hi> Thus are themſelves confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and thus are their tounges divided. Yet ceaſe they not ſtill to plead for Baal, and to bring balme for the ſore of Babel, which cannot be healed. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.8.9.58.64. <hi>with Rev.</hi> 18. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now to proceed, we wil ſhew by the Scriptures, that none of the Miniſters of that Church have the office of Paſtors or Teachers ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. which we prove thus:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Paſtors and Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. have their offices, callings, adminiſtration, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ordeyned by Chriſt in his Teſtament.</p>
               <p>But the Prelates Prieſts &amp; Deacons of the Church of England have not their offices, callings, miniſtration &amp; maintenance ordeyned by Chriſt in his Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Therfore the Prelates Prieſts &amp; Deacons of the church of England are not Paſtors &amp; Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>The truth of the Propoſition appeareth by that place of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.8.11.12. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>and</hi> 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.28. <hi>Heb. .5.</hi>4. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.13.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>and</hi> 3. <hi>chap. and</hi> 22.18.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.2. <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.5. <hi>and</hi> 9.14. <hi>and</hi> 11.23.24.25.26. <hi>and</hi> 12.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>and throughout the Epiſtles to Timothee and Titus: with other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ike Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth of the Aſſumption appeareth by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4135:7"/>
and practiſe, inaſmuch as their offices of <hi>Prelacy, Prieſthood, &amp; Deaconry;</hi> their calling &amp; entrance according to their Pontificall and Book of conſecrating Biſhops and Archbiſhops and ordering Prieſts and Deacons, as alſo that which ſome of them pretend to have by the <note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <p>Mr. Hilderſ. letter ſect. 10. Mr. Iacobs compariſon of Mariage and Paſtorall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
                     <p>His Reaſons for neceſsity of reformation. pag. 50.</p>
                     <p>Offer of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. pag. 39.</p>
                  </note> choiſe acceptance and conſent of their people, who ſtand themſelves vnder Antichriſt, and vnſeparated from the world, and are no true viſible Churches of Chriſt; their miniſtration by their owne and other popiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Articles, Injunctions, and Book of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer; their Maintenance by Tithes, Lordſhips, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were never ordeyned by Chriſt for his Miniſterie of the Goſpell, but derived from Antichriſt and his apoſtaſie, as hath been proved<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>The Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
                     <p>The Refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mr. Giff.</p>
                     <p>Anſw. to Mr. Hilderſ.</p>
                     <p>And to Mr. Iacob.</p>
                     <p>The Apologie, &amp;c.</p>
                  </note> by vs in divers Treatiſes publiſhed heretofore. And if they ſtill be otherwiſe mynded, it lyeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to ſhew that Chriſt in his Teſtament hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed theſe their offices &amp; things aforeſaid for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie. Which none of them have yet done, nor ever wilbe able to do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Againe, The Miniſterie of Paſtors &amp; Teachers, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. is the ordinarie and perpetual miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie given by Chriſt to his Church, &amp; ſuch as the Princes of the earth neyther may nor ever ſhalbe able to aboliſh, ſeing Chriſt hath appointed it to continue to the end of the world. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.12.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5.7.8. <hi>and</hi> 13.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. and</hi> 5.17. <hi>and</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>with Mat.</hi> 28.20.</p>
               <p>But the Prelacy Prieſthood &amp; Deaconry of the church of England, is not the ordinarie and perpetual Miniſterie given by Chriſt to his Church, but ſuch as the Princes of the earth may and ought to aboliſh out of their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>with</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 23.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4135:7"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2.3.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.1. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Therfore the Prelacy Prieſthood and Deaconry of the Church of England is not the Miniſterie of Paſtors and Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Alſo, The offices of Paſtors &amp; Teachers ordeyned by Chriſt in his Teſtament, are ſuch as did and could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tand with and vnder the offices of Apoſtles Prophets &amp; Evangeliſts, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.4.6.22.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.17.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.7.17.23. <hi>Epiſt. to Tim. &amp; Tit.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>and</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the offices of the Prelates Prieſts and Deacons of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Church of England, are not ſuch as did or could ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith or vnder the offices of Apoſtles Prophets &amp; Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſts. Which if any deny, let them ſhew the contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the ſcriptures. Light hath no fellowſhip with darknes, nor Chriſt with Antichriſt. [And ſuppoſe the Apoſtles were alive in their perſons (as they are in their writings) and were in England, it were worth the knowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they and the ordinances given by them ſhould give place to the Prelates and their Canons and conſtitutions, and whether they ſhould be ſuffred to preach the Goſpel and miniſter the Sacraments without acknowledging the Prelates authority, ſubſcribing to their Articles, wearing of the Surplice, ſigning with the Croſſe in Baptiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for if we look to their<note n="*" place="margin">Canons of the yeare, 1603. Can. 6.7.14 30.36.37.50.57.58 &amp;c.</note> Canons, Lawes, practiſe, and Church-conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theſe tel all men playnely, they muſt yeeld vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that vnder payne of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>ipſo facto, &amp;c.</hi> Not to ſpeak of their impriſoning, &amp; perſecuting of ſuch as witnes the truth againſt them eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto death.]</p>
               <p>Therfore they are not the Paſtors and Teachers or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned by Chriſt in his Teſtament.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Moreover, The offices of true Paſtors and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, are by the ordinance of Chriſt ſet in the Church,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4135:8"/>
and employed in the Miniſtery of the word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Church goverment, ſo as they may not (with their eccleſiaſtical functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) receiv civil offices &amp; callings, nor take vnto them princely titles &amp; dignityes. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2.3.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.5.8.28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13.15.16. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.14. <hi>and</hi> 22.25.26.</p>
               <p>But the offices of the Prelates Prieſts and Deacons of the Church of England, are not ſo: but by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution are ſet in that Church, and employed in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the word Sacraments &amp; Church government, ſo as they may alſo (together with their eccleſiaſtical fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) receive civill offices and callings, (as to be Iuſtices of peace, County palatines, Lords of the Counſel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) &amp; take vnto them Princely titles and dignityes (as of Grace, Lordſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>). Which al men ſee and know to be thus.</p>
               <p>Therfore they are not true Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Againe, The Miniſtery of Chriſtian Paſtors &amp; Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, ſtandeth by the word and ordinance of Chriſt, ſo as al Churches vnder heaven are bound to receive &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit therevnto, and to no other whatſoever. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.12.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5.6.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.5.28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. and</hi> 5.17. <hi>and</hi> 6.13.14.</p>
               <p>But the Prelacy Prieſthood &amp; Deaconry of the Church of England ſtandeth onely by the authority and Law of man, ſo as other Churches els where neyther ar nor need to be ſubject therevnto. Which even themſelves of all ſorts have acknowledged. For which, ſee, <hi>Whitgifts De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in the Preface. The Anſwer to the Abſtract, pag.</hi> 58. <hi>The Admon to the Parliam. The Defence of godly Minist. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therfore their Prelacy Prieſthood &amp; Deaconry is not the Miniſtery of Chriſtian Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4135:8"/>6. Furthermore, The offices of Paſtors and Teachers which Chriſt hath appointed, are ſuch as they which have them muſt be members of a true viſible Church, and bound to one particular Congregation for the Miniſtery &amp; governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4.5.6.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.5.8.12.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.28. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, <hi>4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the offices of the Prelates Prieſts and Deacons of the Church of England are ſuch as they which have them need not be (neyther in their eſtate can be) mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a true viſible Church, but of a falſe, nor are bound to one particular Congregation for the Miniſterie &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement thereof, but the Prelates are over whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and Dioceſes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the other inferiour Prieſts may have (in that eſtate) plurality of benefices &amp; eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall cures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which none can deny.</p>
               <p>Therefore they are not the Paſtors &amp; Teachers which Chriſt hath appointed.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Finally, The offices condition and government of Paſtors and Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. are ſuch as no way empaire the authority Supremacy or dignity of Kings or any other civil Magiſtrates, eyther in civil or ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cauſes. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>and Rom.</hi> 12.7, 8. <hi>with</hi> 13.1. <hi>&amp; Tit.</hi> 1.5, 9. <hi>with</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. <hi>with</hi> 2.13.14.</p>
               <p>But the offices condition &amp; government of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates Prieſts and Deacons of the Church of England, are ſuch as do many wayes empaire the authoritie ſupremacy and dignity of Kings and all other Magiſtrates, both in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill &amp; eccleſiaſticall cauſes. And for an inſtance take theſe particulars, That <hi>the Prelates will have their preſence, voyce, &amp; authority to be at Parliaments, for enacting of Lawes &amp; ſtatutes for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, &amp;c.</hi> That <hi>they are rulers of whole Provinces &amp; Dioceſes in the eccleſiasticall cauſes therof;</hi> That <hi>in civill eſtate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4135:9"/>
and government, ſome of them are above all, and all of them above ſome of the Nobles, Iuſtices, and other Magistrates of the land;</hi> That <hi>themſelves, their Courts, and officers, handle &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine ſundry civill cauſes and affaires pertayning to the civill Magiſtracy;</hi> That <hi>they inflict civil mulcts and punishments;</hi> That <hi>in their forbidden times they give licences to matry, &amp;c.</hi> That <hi>the beneficed Priests ſweare Canonical obedience to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates;</hi> That <hi>all the Prieſts and Deacons are exempt from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates iuriſdiction in divers things apperteyning vnto them, and anſwerable onely or chiefly to the Prelates and their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore they are not the Paſtors and Teachers ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>And to this end might divers other reaſons be alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from particular conſideration of theſe ſeverall offices. As for example, if any for the Prelates would perſwade, that their Archbiſhops have the Paſtors office, then would it follow that they have but two Paſtors in the land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have but two Archbiſhops. Or if they ſay, the Lordbiſhops be Paſtors, then have they but ſixe and twenty or thereabout: and what office then have the Archbiſhops above them?</p>
               <p>If others ſay, the Prieſts (whether Parſons, Vicars, or Stipendaries) be Paſtors, then let them tell vs what of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their Archbiſhops &amp; Lordbiſhops have amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, ſeing Chriſt hath appointed in his Church no ordinarie eccleſiaſticall office for any one perſon, greater then the Paſtors; nor ſet the Paſtors one of them above another in any reſpect of Miniſtery power or government, but made them all equall therein. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1.8.12.18. <hi>and</hi> 3.1.7.14. <hi>with Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17.28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>and Luk.</hi> 22.24.25, 26, 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4135:9"/>And thus much is acknowledged and publiſhed alſo by ſome of themſelves, both heretofore in divers of their books, and now of late in an Offer of conference about certayne Propoſitions, which they offer to mainteyne againſt the Prelates: Among which are theſe, namely, <note n="*" place="margin">Offer of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That <hi>the Paſtor of a particular Congregation is the higheſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie eccleſiaſticall Officer in any true conſtituted viſible Church of Chriſt;</hi> That <hi>it is the office of every true Paſtor to teach and to governe ſpiritually onely one Church or Congregation immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnder Christ;</hi> That <hi>it is ſimply vnlawful for any Paſtor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the new Teſtament to be alſo a civil Magistrate;</hi> That <hi>the Office and calling of Provinciall and Dioceſan Prelates is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the word of God; &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore, if any would ſay, their Deacons have the Paſtors office, the ſame abſurdity followeth as in the former: and this moreover, that the works of the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons office are by the Apoſtles oppoſed to the work of the Miniſtery, wherein the Paſtors office is employed. <hi>Act. 6.2.3.4. with Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe if they would ſay, they have the Teachers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, it would be knowen whether it be the Archbiſhops, Lordbiſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, Parſons, Vicars, or Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendaries, that have it among them; &amp; to whom they are adjoyned for the work of Miniſterie, as<note n="‖" place="margin">Ephe. 4.11.12. Rom. 12.7.8.</note> the Teachers are to Paſtors, ſeing they have none in the office of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, ſpoken of <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. as is proved here before; and what office of Miniſtery the reſt of their Prelates Prieſts &amp; Deacons have whom themſelves account not to have the Teachers office; and whether the Teachers ſpoken of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 4.11. muſt firſt be Deacons, and then Prieſts, and promiſe obedience to the Prelates, &amp; that alſo as to their Ordinaries, and be ſilenced and depoſed at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4135:10"/>But of theſe things we have ſpoken in other Treatiſes, to which we refer the Reader. <hi>Refut.</hi> of Mr. <hi>Giff. pag.</hi> 104.105.106. <hi>&amp;c. Anſw. to Mr Hilderſ. pag.</hi> 79.80-87-94. <hi>&amp;c. Anſw. to Mr. Iacob. pag.</hi> 188. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whereas ſome alledge, for warrant of hearing theſe Miniſters, that the people were to hearken to <hi>the Scribes and Phariſees ſitting in Moſes ſeat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 23.2.3. it is to be noted, that they were Levites, Prieſts, expounders of the Law, and Iudges of the pleas and controverſies of Iſrael; And therfore had the true of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices &amp; ordinances, which the Lord by Moſes did appoint for teaching and governing of that Church: as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth both by the phraſe it ſelf <hi>of ſitting on Moſes chaire,</hi> and by conference of theſe and the like Scriptures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.8,—12. <hi>and</hi> 33.1.<hi>8.</hi>10. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.8.9. <hi>and</hi> 19.<hi>8,</hi>—11. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.4, <hi>8. and</hi> 9.3.4.<hi>5. with Mat.</hi> 22.34.35.41. <hi>and</hi> 23. <hi>chap. Mar.</hi> 12.28.32.35. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.19.24. <hi>and</hi> 3.1.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.34. This then is nothing at all for any falſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, never ordeyned by the Lord: ſuch as the preſent Miniſterie of the Church of England is proved to be.</p>
               <p>Beſides, to be a Phariſee, was not to have a new kind of Miniſterie, but to be of a ſpeciall ſect among the Iewes that pretended more ſtrict obſervation of the Law then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.5. <hi>and</hi> 26.5. And they were of any of their tribes, or of the proſelyte Gentiles: as may be ſeen in Paul, who was a Phariſee, of the tribe of Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.<hi>6.</hi> and in them that were ſent to Iohn Baptiſt, who were Phariſees of the tribe of Levi, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſts and Levites, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.19.24. and in the Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte Gentiles, brought ſo to be by the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, ſpoken of <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.15.</p>
               <p>And further, although they were verie corrupt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4135:10"/>
(notwithſtanding all the pretence they made) ſo as Chriſt taught his diſciples<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.6.12. and 23. chap. Luk 12.1.</note> to take heed of the leven of their doctrine, and of their hypocriſy, and wickednes in converſation: yet did they ſtill hold, that every true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery muſt be from heaven and not of men, and vrged Iohn the Baptiſt to warrant his calling and Miniſterie by the Scriptures: <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.1-7. <hi>with Ioh.</hi> 1.19.—27. So far were they themſelves from admitting any falſe miniſtery, not appointed by God and approved in his word.</p>
               <p>And this alſo have the forward preachers acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and proved heretofore againſt the Prelates: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by their owne words, ſaying,<note n="‖" place="margin">T. C. firſt reply pag. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>The miniſterie is by the word of God and heavenly, and not left to the will of men to deviſe at their pleaſure: as appeareth by that which is noted of Iohn, where the Phariſees coming to Iohn Baptiſt, after that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to be eyther Chriſt, or Elias, or another Prophet,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 1.23.</note> 
                  <hi>conclude:</hi> If thou be neyther Chriſt, nor Elias, nor of the Prophets, why baptizeſt thou? <hi>Which had bene no good argument, if S. Iohn might have ben of ſome other function then of thoſe which were ordinarie in the Church and inſtituted of God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he to eſtablish his ſingular &amp; extraordinarie functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alledgeth the word of God: whereby appeareth, that as it was not lawfull to bring in any ſtrange dostrine, ſo was it</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>not lawfull to teach the true doctrine, vnder the name of any other function then was inſtituted by God. Let the whole practiſe of the Church vnder the Law be looked vpon, and it ſhall not be found that any other eccleſiaſticall miniſtery was appointed, then thoſe orders of hy prieſts and Levites &amp;c. which wer appointed by the law of God. And if there were any raiſed vp extraordinarily, the ſame had their calling confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from heaven, eyther by ſignes or miracles, or by playn and cleare teſtimonies of the mouth of God, or by extraordinarie exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; movings of the Spirit of God. So that it appeareth that the miniſterie of the Goſpell and the functions thereof ought to be from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4135:11"/>
heaven and of God, and not invented by the brayne of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have themſelves written heretofore: and thus doth their owne teſtimonie agree with the word of God againſt their preſent eſtate and their woonted allegations for their continuing therein. But of theſe things alſo we have ſpoken other where: and wil not here further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them. <hi>Treatiſe of the Miniſt. of Engl. p.</hi> 54.55. <hi>&amp;c. Anſw. to Mr. Iacob. p.</hi> 195.</p>
               <p>The concluſion of all is this, that ſeing the Lord himſelf, aſcending vp on high, hath given offices of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie to his Church, calling &amp; requiring all his people to heare &amp; have ſpirituall communion with them, &amp; not with any other; and ſeing the preſent miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England cannot be warranted by the word of God to be that which Chriſt hath given, and ſet in his Church, for the work of his Miniſterie, we may not therefore in the worſhip of God heare or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate therewith, vnder any colour whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4135:11"/>
               <head>The ſecond Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>NOne may heare or have any ſpirituall communion with the Miniſtery of Antichriſts apostaſie:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore none may heare or have any ſpirtual communion with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>THe Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or firſt part of this Reaſon is manifeſt: 1. Becauſe all falſe Miniſteries are forbidden by the Lord, and ſtand vnder the denunciation of his curſe: <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4.5. <hi>with Deut.</hi> 18.9-15. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.19-25. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.9.10.11. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.2-6. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3-12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. <hi>and</hi> 17. <hi>chap.</hi> 2 <hi>Iohn. ver.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.26. <hi>and</hi> 27.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe we are commanded to go out of Babylon, and not to partake with any of her ſinns, &amp; therfore not with the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.5.6. <hi>with Ier.</hi> 51.6.9.45. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14-17. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.1-6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe by hearing and communicating with ſuch a Miniſterie, all that do ſo, become the ſervants of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, as it is written, <hi>His ſeruants ye are to whom ye obey,</hi> &amp; thus become ſubject to the wrath of God: <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>with Rev.</hi> 14.9.10.11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe to heare or joyne with that Miniſterie, is to honour and conſpire with Antichriſt againſt Chriſt, and what in vs vs lyeth to vphold that which the Lord will conſume. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 14.9-12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.4.5.6.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4135:12"/>5. Becauſe this is not to obey the Goſpel and receive the love of the truth that we may be ſaved, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to ſend vs ſtrong deluſions to beleev lyes and pleaſe our ſelves in vnrighteouſnes, being carryed away in the deceitfulnes thereof among them that periſh, vnto condemnation. For thus the ſcripture ſpeaketh of ſuch as in religion yeeld ſubmiſſion to Antichriſt the man of ſinne in his apoſtaſie. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.9.10.11.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6-12. <hi>and</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
               <p>THe Aſſumption or ſecond part of the Reaſon is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by divers Arguments, as followeth.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>The first Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">I.</note>THe Miniſterie of Deacons and Prieſts ordeyned by the Prelates therevnto, is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is the Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts ordeyned by the Prelates therevnto:</item>
                     <item>Therfore the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition of this Argument is proved <hi>firſt</hi> thus:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Miniſterie of Deacons and Prieſts which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it ſelf to be Chriſts, &amp; yet was not ſet by Chriſt in his Church for the work of his Miniſtery, that is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</p>
                  <p>But the Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts ordeyned by the Prelates therevnto, accounts it ſelf to be Chriſts, and yet was not ſet by Chriſt in his Church for the work of his Miniſterie:</p>
                  <p>Therfore the Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Prelates therevnto, is the Miniſtery of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts Apoſtaſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4135:12"/>The Propoſition none can deny.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption hath two parts: The one, that <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Deacons and Prieſts ordeyned by the Prelates therevnto, accounts it ſelf to be Christs Miniſtery:</hi> Which themſelves will graunt. The other, that <hi>this was not ſet by Chriſt in his Church for the work of his Miniſtery:</hi> Which is proved alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the firſt Reaſon here before, and in other Reaſons hereafter following.</p>
                  <p>Agayne, the Propoſition of the Argument is proved <hi>ſecondly</hi> thus:</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have ſuch offices &amp; government, as be ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts apoſtaſie, then the Miniſtery ordeyned by them therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, muſt needs be the Miniſtery of that Apoſtaſie:</p>
                  <p>But the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and government, as be ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</p>
                  <p>Therfore the Miniſtery ordeyned by them is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</p>
                  <p>The conſequence of the Propoſition is manifeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the fruit muſts needs be ſuch as is the tree: Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do men gather grapes of thornes, or figs of thiſtles. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16.17.18. And who can bring a cleane thing out of filthynes? Not any one. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.4.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proved <hi>first</hi> thus:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſoever (beſides Chriſt Ieſus himſelf) have ſuch offices and government as thereby they clayme to be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Lords, they have the offices and government which are ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts apoſtaſie, &amp; are indeed very Antichriſts themſelves:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4135:13"/>But the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices &amp; government as thereby they clayme to be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Lords:</p>
                  <p>Therfore the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have the offices and government, which are ſpeciall parts of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts apoſtaſie, and are indeed very Antichriſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>The Propoſition is proved by the Scriptures, which teach that there is but one Lord, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>Ephe. 4.5.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>and</hi> 12.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.18. <hi>with Pſal.</hi> 110.1. <hi>Micah,</hi> 5.2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.12.13.14.27. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.22.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.37. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.11.12.13. <hi>and</hi> 2.1. <hi>and</hi> 3.1.7. Now that theſe Scriptures and the like do ſpeak of a ſpirituall Lord, is playne both by the circumſtances of the places themſelves, and becauſe the Scripture other where giveth allowance of many civil or temporal Lords, but no where of any ſpirituall Lord, ſave Ieſus Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, whoſe kingdome is not of this world. <hi>Gen.</hi> 40.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 45.8. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.16. <hi>and</hi> 26.17. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149 8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 25.26. <hi>and</hi> 26.25 <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26 <hi>and</hi> 2.8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.13.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. <hi>and</hi> 19.16. <hi>compared with the Scriptures here cited before.</hi> And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, whoſoever is a ſpirituall Lord, he may require ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall honour to be yeelded vnto him, and hath the Spirit of God to give vnto his people, and through him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by it can ſanctifie them and their actions and ſervice of his Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which things who is there that can require and effect, but onely the Lord himſelf? And who then can be a ſpirituall Lord, but he alone? So as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo it appeareth, that all other which take vpon them to be ſpirituall Lords, are indeed very Antichriſts.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proved by the Lawes and Statutes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4135:13"/>
of the Land, whoſe words be theſe, <hi>Be it enacted by the Kings most excellent Maieſtie, the Lords Spirituall and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled:</hi> For by <hi>the Lords ſpirituall</hi> is meant here the Prelates. And to the ſame end it is to be obſerved, that in their Canons and practiſe they take vpon them, as if they were ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Lords, not onely to preſcribe their own ordinances to the Church for the worſhip of God, but alſo to bynd the ſpirit and conſcience to the acknowledgment and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation thereof; and yet further in their ordination of Prieſts even to give the holy Ghoſt, ſaying to the Prieſts when they ordeyne them, <hi>Receive the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> as if it were in their power to give the Spirit of God to whom they would, or that they were authorized here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by Ieſus Chriſt, who onely is the ſpirituall Lord of his Church, and giveth his ſpirit according to his own will, to whom and as it pleaſeth him. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14.16. <hi>and</hi> 15.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.5.6.7. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.7.1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20.27.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption aforeſaid is proved <hi>ſecondly</hi> thus:</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The offices and government of ſuch Biſhops as are over Dioceſan and Provinciall Churches, and exerciſe eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction over all the Miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therein, are ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</p>
                  <p>But the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and government of ſuch Biſhops as are over Dioceſan and Provinciall Churches, and exerciſe eccleſiaſticall ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction over all the Miniſters and people therein:</p>
                  <p>Therfore the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have ſuch offices and government, as be ſpeciall parts of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts apoſtaſie.</p>
                  <p>The Propoſition is evident, inaſmuch as the offices &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4135:14"/>
government of ſuch Biſhops, and ſubjection of ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Churches, are onely to be found in Antichriſts apoſtaſie, and were never appointed by Chriſt or his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. For now in the tyme of the Goſpell, Chriſt hath ſet no other forme of viſible Churches to which he hath given offices of Miniſtery, but onely particular congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, ſuch as may come together in one, and joyntly perform all publick dutyes layd vpon them by the word of God. As may appeare by the conſtitution of<note n="†" place="margin">Act. 1.15. &amp; 2.41.42. with 6.2.3.5 6. &amp; 11.22. and 15.22.23. &amp; 21.17 18.22. And 13.1.2. &amp; 14.23. &amp; 16 4.5. and 20.17.28. And the epiſtles to the Rom. Cor. Gal. Ephe. Phil. Col. Theſ. &amp;c.</note> all the Churches planted by the Apoſtles, and written unto by them in ſo many ſeverall epiſtles: alſo by the Churches to whom Chriſt wrote by Iohn in the Revelation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.11. <hi>with</hi> 2. <hi>and</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> Other formes of Churches therefore no men have power to inſtitute. And when &amp; where they are erected, what other can they be but An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian?</p>
                  <p>And as for the examples of <hi>Timothee, Titus,</hi> and the like, vſually alleged for defence of the Prelates authority and juriſdiction, they will nothing help them. For theſe were Evangeliſts, which the Prelates are not: as we have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> former Reaſon. And the particular Churches have in themſelves ech of them full intereſt and power from Chriſt to enjoy and practiſe all his ordinances, for Miniſtery, worſhip, government, and whatſoever he hath given his Church to be obſerved therein to the end of the world. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17-20. <hi>and</hi> 28.20. <hi>with Act.</hi> 6.3-6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.17.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4-8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21.22.23. <hi>and</hi> 4.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.4.11.12. <hi>and</hi> 11.2.23.24.25.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.33.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>and</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.11.<hi>20. with</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And wheras the extraordinary offices of Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts, are ceaſed; yet<note n="‡" place="margin">Ioh. 15.16. The Acts and Epistles of the Apostles. &amp;c.</note> their fruit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth ſtill: and we have the benefit of it for our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4135:14"/>
by their writings, which the Churches then had by their bodily preſence. To which end may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved alſo, how<note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.1. Phil. 1.1. Col. 1.1. Philem. ver. 1.</note> ſome of the epiſtles are written in the Name of Paul, &amp; Timothee <hi>(an Apoſtle, and an Evangelist);</hi> and<note n="‖" place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.1. &amp; 2 Theſ. 1.1</note> ſome of them in the Name of Paul, Silvanus, and Timothee (<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.9. <hi>1</hi> Tim. 2.7.</note> 
                     <hi>an Apoſtle,</hi>
                     <note n="‡" place="margin">Silvanus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame with Silas, as is like by the Name, the placing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Act. 15.32.40. and 16.19. and 17.4.10.14.15. &amp; 18.5.</note> 
                     <hi>a Prophet, and an</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Evangeliſt):</hi> which three alſo are ioyned togither for the conſtant tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of one and the ſame truth in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. And withall, that the Apoſtles did then ſo write and mind, as purpoſely intending the inſtructions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements given by them ſhould be obſerved of all Churches, both of the Miniſters and other members thereof according to their places, to the end of the world. (<hi>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 12.3-8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.23-26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.37. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.9. <hi>and</hi> 6.16.17. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3 <hi>chap. and</hi> 4.11.12.13. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23-29. <hi>and</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.16.17. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14.15. <hi>and</hi> 5.21. <hi>and</hi> 6.3.5.13.14. <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>and</hi> 3.1.15.16.17. <hi>and</hi> 4.5.6. <hi>Titus Epiſt. Heb.</hi> 2.1-4. <hi>and</hi> 3.1-6. <hi>and</hi> 13.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12-21. <hi>and</hi> 2.1. <hi>and</hi> 3.1.2.3.15.16. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1.12.13.14. <hi>and</hi> 4.1-6. <hi>Iude, ver.</hi> 3.17.18.19.20.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>chap. and</hi> 22.18.19.20.) So as now there can be no need or lawfull vſe of any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan, Provinciall, Nationall, or Vniverſall Biſhops.</p>
                  <p>And for any reaſon or proof that the Prelates or any for them have brought or can bring from the Scripture for their Prelacy, it will aſwell follow that as they have now their Biſhops over Dioceſes, and Archbiſhops over Provinces; ſo if the King would, he might have a Primate or Archprelate over all his Dominions; and if there were a Monarch over Europe, he might have a Patriarch over all the Prelates therein; and ſo an Emperour over the world (if there were any) might alſo have an Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menicall or Vniverſall Biſhop and Pope over all the reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4135:15"/>And <hi>Timothees</hi> example would aſwel warrant theſe, as it will the other: ſeing there was not any Church in the world, whither his office and the dutyes therof might not extend, as his calling and employment was. Of whom the Scripture ſheweth, that he was, and did the dutyes of his office, ſometimes in one part of the world, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes in another, ſometymes in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and ſometymes in <hi>Europe:</hi> as may be ſeen by the countreyes where he was at ſundry tymes: As in Aſia, being in divers countreyes and parts thereof, in <hi>Phrygia, Galatia, Myſia, Ionia, &amp;c.</hi> And in Europe likewiſe, in <hi>Macedonia, Achaia, Italie, &amp;c.</hi> And in theſe countreyes and nations, ſometymes in one city and with one church, and ſometymes with another, as namely, at <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> at <hi>Philippi, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo ſometymes being with the Apoſtle Paul where he was himſelf, ſometymes left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him when he went other whither, ſometymes ſent for to come vnto him to ſuch place as he appointed, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes ſent away from him to other places where he would employ him, &amp;c. And this, ſometymes to bring the Churches into a ſetled order according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles direction, ſometymes to ſtabliſh and comfort them being already in ſuch eſtate, ſometymes to know their ſtate, and to put them in remembrance of the Apoſtles wayes, ſometymes to look that none taught otherwiſe, but that the doctrine and order delivered by the Apoſtles were reteyned among them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By all which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, both what the office and employment of an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt was, and that Timothee was not a Biſhop in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry office, perteyning to any one certayne place &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but an Evangeliſt in extraoadinary function, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed ſometymes in one countrey &amp; part of the world, and ſometymes in another, ſometimes with one Church
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4135:15"/>
and people, and ſometymes with another, according as he had direction &amp; appointment by the Apoſtle Paul, whoſe companion and aſſiſtant he was. For all which, ſee theſe Scriptures, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. <hi>chap. and</hi> 17.14.15. <hi>and</hi> 18.5. <hi>and</hi> 19.22. <hi>and</hi> 20.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>and</hi> 16.10.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. <hi>and</hi> 2.19.22.23. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.1.2.6. <hi>with both the Epistles written by Paul vnto Timothee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like may be obſerved concerning <hi>Titus,</hi> who was ſometymes with the Apoſtle Paul himſelf, ſometymes left behind him when he departed other whither, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes called vnto him, ſometymes ſent away from him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being thus ſometymes in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſometymes in <hi>Aſia:</hi> And in Europe being alſo at divers places, as at <hi>Corinth in Achaia;</hi> at <hi>Rome in Italie;</hi> in <hi>Creta; Dalmatia, &amp;c.</hi> And in Aſia likewiſe, at <hi>Ieruſalem in Iudea,</hi> at <hi>Nicopolis in Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, &amp;c.</hi> As appeareth by theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23.24. <hi>and</hi> 12.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.1. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.4.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.12. <hi>with the whole Epistle to Titus.</hi> And the like may be ſeen alſo in <hi>Marcus, Ariſtarchus, Tychicus, &amp; others,</hi> whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples they might aſwel alledge as thoſe of Timothee &amp; Titus. <hi>Act.</hi> 12.25. <hi>and</hi> 13.5. <hi>and</hi> 15.37.39. <hi>and</hi> 20.4.5. <hi>and</hi> 27. 2. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.21.22. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.7.8.10.11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.11.12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Philem. ver</hi> 24.</p>
                  <p>But by ſuch allegations they let all men know how near they are driven, that can fynd no warrant in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for Dioceſan and Provinciall Biſhops, and therefore are glad to lay hold on the Evangeliſts office in <hi>Timothee</hi> and <hi>Titus:</hi> from which notwithſtanding they and their Churches and Miniſters are as farr as cloudy darknes is from the cleare light of the Sun. For the further decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof, beſides that which hath ben ſayd here before and in other Treatiſes written of this argument, I will by way of queſtion propound ſome things to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4135:16"/>
by ſuch as are of judgement, which as they ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be found may give more light to theſe and other poynts ſometymes called in queſtion. The things are theſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whether the ordinance of Chriſt be not ſuch, as therein they which be in the greater offices, have (beſides their owne peculiar function wherevnto they ought to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) power and authority both themſelves to performe the dutyes of any the inferiour offices, when there is juſt and needfull occaſion, and to look that they be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by all ſuch as they are ſpecially layd vpon, for the better ſervice of the Lord and his church therein.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether on the contrary, the apoſtaſie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt be not ſuch (touching the Miniſtery and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church) as therein they which be in the leſſer offices have power and authority among them to exceed the dutyes of the office which Chriſt hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; to performe the dutyes apperteyning to the higher offices: by meanes whereof both Antichriſt hath riſen vp to ſo great a height, and ſo many orders and degrees of ſuperior and inferior Miniſters have bene received and ſtill are reteyned in that degenerate eſtate and apoſtaſie of the man of ſinne, as is come to paſſe.</p>
                  <p>And touching the firſt, becauſe the offices ſet by Chriſt in his Church be of two ſorts, ſome extraordinary and for a tyme and ſpeciall vſe, ſome ordinary and prrpetual: whether it be true in both, or in the firſt, and in them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. As for example, That <hi>the Apostles,</hi> who were in the greateſt office ordeyned by Chriſt vnder the Goſpel, <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 28.18.19.20. Ephe. 4.11.12. 1 Cor. 12.28.</note> had (beſides the peculiar office of Apoſtleſhip) the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alſo and authority of the other Offices of<note n="‖" place="margin">Act. 20.29.30 Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 11.25.26. 2 Theſ. 2.3-8. 1 Tim. 4.1.2.3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Pet. 2. &amp; 3. chap. <hi>1</hi> Ioh. 2.18. Iude, ver. 17.18.</note> Prophets,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4135:16"/>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 8.14.25. &amp; 14.7. &amp; 15.35.36 41. &amp; 16.40. Rom. 1.11.12.15.</note> Evangeliſts,<note n="‡" place="margin">Ioh. 21.16. Act. 1.40.42. &amp; 20.2. 1 Cor. 9.7.</note> Paſtors,<note n="†" place="margin">Act. 5 42. 1 Tim. 2.7. 2 Tim. 1.11.</note> Teachers,<note n="‖" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.1. Act. 6.2.6. &amp; 15.6.22. 1 Tim. 4.14. with 2 Tim, 1.6.</note> Elders &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 4.34.35. &amp; 6.2.3 4. &amp; 11.29.30. 1 Cor. 16.3.4. Gal. 2.10.</note> Deacons, both to performe them vpon juſt occaſion themſelves, &amp; to ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> performed by others as is aforeſayd; For which, conſider the Scriptures here quoted in the Margent.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe, that <hi>the Prophets</hi> (beſides their owne ſpecial office) had in them the power &amp; authority of the other inferiour offices of Evangeliſts, Paſtors, Teachers, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.32.40.41. <hi>and</hi> 17.15. <hi>and</hi> 18.5.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.5.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
                  <p>And in like ſort, that <hi>the Evangelists</hi> (beſides their owne peculiar function) had in them the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the other ſmaller offices of Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.35.38. <hi>with</hi> 21.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.6.16.17.23. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. <hi>with the Epist. to Tim. &amp; Tit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And, it being ſo in the ordinary offices likewiſe, that <hi>the Paſtors</hi> therefore (beſides their own peculiar function) have in them the power and authority of the other ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary offices of the Teachers, Elders, and Deacons, for performance and overſight as is aforeſaid. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe.</hi> 4.11.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1-15. <hi>and</hi> 5.17.22. <hi>with</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2.3.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.42. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. <hi>with</hi> 2.1.8.12.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.1.7.14.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe that the <hi>Teachers</hi> have in them (beſides their owne ſpeciall office) the power and authority of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders and Deacons. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8.9.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.8.12.28. <hi>Ephe</hi> 4.11.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.—15. <hi>and</hi> 5.17. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5-9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7.17.</p>
                  <p>And in like maner, that <hi>the Elders</hi> (beſides their owne ſpeciall functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) have in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power &amp; authority of the Deacons office, for the doing and overſeing thereof as before is ſpoken. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.29.30. <hi>and</hi> 20.17, 28. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.13.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1-15. <hi>and</hi> 5.17-22. <hi>with</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2.3.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4135:17"/>Finally, that the <hi>Deacons,</hi> as alſo the reſt aforeſayd, have (beſides their owne peculiar office) right and power to enjoy whatſoever intereſt the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have in the Church, for any dutyes or actions to be performed therein, according to their place and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And further, that when they ſhall have miniſtred well in the Deacons office, they may be called afore o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the brethren into the higher offices of the Elders, being endued with giftes therevnto. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4-8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12-28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8-13.</p>
                  <p>But now on the contrary, when ſuch as were in the inferiour offices, conteyned not themſelves within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of their callings, but took vpon themſelves or had layd vpon them by others power and authority of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour functions, then ſprung vp the apoſtaſie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in the churches miniſtery and government. As namely, when the Paſtors and Biſhops of particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations came to have authority &amp; overſight over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches and over the Miniſters and people therein, in a kind of reſemblance of the extraordinary offices al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ceaſed: <hi>Contrarie to Rev.</hi> 1.11.12.13.20. <hi>with</hi> 2.1.8.12 18. <hi>and</hi> 3.1.7.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2.3.4. And that the ruling Elders or Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (now called Prieſts) did the Miniſteriall dutyes of the Paſtors and Teachers in the particular Congregations: <hi>Contrary to Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. And that the Deacons alſo baptized, and were Miniſters of the word; which the Apoſtles did purpoſely oppoſe to the dutyes of that office at the inſtitution thereof. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2.3.4. So as of theſe things it may be ſayd, as Chriſt did in another caſe, <hi>From the beginning it was not ſo. Mat.</hi> 19.8.</p>
                  <p>And herevpon in tyme many ſorts and degrees of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſervile Miniſters and ſuperior Lordly Prelates grew
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4135:17"/>
vp &amp; encreaſed in that defection of the Man of ſinne, till Antichriſt at the length was exalted in his throne. From which now agayne the Lord hath begunne to bring him downe, diſcovering and conſuming that myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity by the light and power of his Goſpell: and will not ceaſe, till the ſame be fully aboliſhed &amp; caſt into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomles pit, from whence it firſt aroſe. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.7.8.9 10.11.12. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18.19. <hi>with Rev.</hi> 6.12.13.14. <hi>and</hi> 8. <hi>and</hi> 9. <hi>and</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>and</hi> 16. <hi>and</hi> 17. <hi>and</hi> 18. <hi>and</hi> 19. <hi>chap.</hi> And hitherto of the Propoſition of the laſt Syllogiſme.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption thereof (namely, <hi>that the Prelates of the Church of Engl. have the offices and government of ſuch Biſhops as are over Dioceſan and Provinciall Churches, and exerciſe eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall iuriſdiction over all the Ministers and people therein)</hi> is evident by their Church-conſtitution, Lawes, and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. And themſelves neyther will nor can deny it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The other Aſſumption aforeſaid <hi>(viz, that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of the Church of Engl. have ſuch offices and government, as be ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts apoſtaſie)</hi> is proved <hi>thirdly</hi> by this, that the offices and government of the Prelates of the Church of Engl. do not in their nature and proper vſe perteyne to any ſociety body and eſtate, eyther civill or eccleſiaſticall, but onely to the body and kingdome of Antichriſt. Of which, as alſo of other reaſons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the point in hand, more ſhalbe ſpoken hereafter in the ſeverall Arguments following concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And thus much concerning the Propoſition of this Argument.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption of the Argument (namely, <hi>that the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of England is the Miniſterie of Deacons and Prieſts ordeyned by the Prelates
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4135:18"/>
therevnto</hi>) is vndeniably confirmed by the conſtitution, Canons, and obſervation of that Church. And to the end that this poynt may the better be conſidered, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it giveth great light and proof to the whole contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie concerning the Antichriſtianity of their eſtate, I wil here note a few ſpecial things, which (among many other apperteyning to their office &amp; calling) may to this purpoſe be obſerved.</p>
                  <p>Firſt for their <hi>Deacons,</hi> they are at their entrance into that office preſented to the Prelate by an Archdeacon or his deputy, ſaying, <hi>Reverend father in God, I preſent vnto you theſe perſons preſent, to be admitted Deacons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then the Biſhop commending them to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Congregation, with the Clerks &amp; people pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is to ſay or ſing the Letanie and Suffrages, with the communion of the day, and a number of ſtinted prayers &amp; Collects, borrowed from the Papiſts.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They promiſe that they wil reverently obey their Ordinary, &amp; other chief Miniſters of the Church, <hi>that is,</hi> the Lord Biſhop of the Dioces, the Archbiſhop, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, Chancelor, Commiſſarie, &amp; the reſt of that ſort, whoſe offices are Antichriſtian.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. After this promiſe made, they are then ordeyned <hi>Deacons</hi> by the Lord Biſhop or his Suffragane, laying his hands vpon their head, and ſaying, <hi>Take thou authority to execute the office of a Deacon in the Church of God committed vnto thee: in the name of the Father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghost. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. And then the Biſhop delivereth to every one of them the new Teſtament, ſaying, <hi>Take thou authority to read the Goſpel in the Church of God, and to preach the ſame, if thou be therevnto ordinarily commaunded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4135:18"/>6. Then one of them appoynted by the Biſhop, reads the Goſpel of that day: And they al are injoyned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the communion with the Biſhop.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Alſo among the works and duties of their office, they are appoynted to read Homilies and divine ſervice, to inſtruct the youth in the Catechiſme, to Baptiſe, and to preach, if they be admitted thereto by the Biſhop. Whereas it cannot be ſhewed that the Apoſtles ever layd theſe dutyes vpon the Deacons, but ſuch as are<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 6.2.3.4. Rom. 12.8.</note> plainely oppoſed to the miniſterie of the word and prayer, <hi>namely,</hi> the charge of the poor and Church treaſure, for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and diſtribution of the Churches benevolence.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon ſome of themſelves ſeeking reformation have publiſhed heretofore, that<note n="‡" place="margin">Defence of Eccleſ. Diſcip pag. 102.</note> 
                     <hi>their Deaconship is a mere humane institution, a degree to the Priesthood, and nothing like the ordinance of God;</hi> that<note n="†" place="margin">Admon. to Parliam. first treatiſe</note> 
                     <hi>though the name of Deacons be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning among them, yet the office is fowly perverted &amp; turned vpſide downe;</hi> and that<note n="*" place="margin">Defence of godly Minist pag. 108.</note> 
                     <hi>it is manifestly contrarie to the word of God.</hi> The example of <hi>Philip,</hi> who was one of the ſeven Deacons, &amp; preached &amp; baptized (which by ſome is alledged for approbation of their practiſe) wil not help them. For he was in a true and lawfull office, not in an Antichriſtian; he had a lawful calling by the Church, not an vnlawful entrance by Prelates, as theſe have; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; where he was Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Apoſtles miniſtred the word and baptized, neither was he then ordeyned to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof, but attended to the tables of the poor; and afterwards when he preached and baptized, he did the work and office of an Evangeliſt, by which name the Scripture expreſly calleth him. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2-6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.14.40.41.42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.8. <hi>with</hi> 8.5, 6, 7.12, 26, 29. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Next, for the <hi>Priests,</hi> firſt they muſt be <hi>Deacons,</hi> that is,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4135:19"/>
ſet by the Prelates in the office and after the maner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then having continued in that office the ſpace of a yeare (except it ſeem otherwiſe good to the Ordinary) they are agayne preſented to the Biſhop or his Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane, by an Archdeacon or his deputy, ſaying, <hi>Reverend father in God, I preſent theſe perſons preſent to be admitted to the Order of Prieſthood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Afterward there followeth the Letany, and ſome Collects and ſtinted prayers taken out of the Popes pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall: with an exhortation, an Epiſtle and Goſpell, wherein they abuſe and pervert the Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Then the Prelate aſketh them, <hi>Do you think in your hart that you be truly called according to the wil of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the order of this Church of England, to the Miniſtery of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood?</hi> And the partyes that are to be ordeyned, anſwer, every one for himſelf, <hi>I think it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. At which tyme alſo they promiſe agayne, reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obey their Ordinary &amp; other chief Miniſters of the Church, that is the Prelates and other Officers aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. So after a few queſtions made, and prayers read, they kneel downe vpon their knees at the Prelates feet, &amp; he with the Prieſts preſent lay hands ſeverally vpon the head of every one of them that receiveth orders, ſaying vnto them, <hi>Receive the holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſinnes thou doeſt forgive, they are forgiven: and whoſe ſinnes thou doeſt reteyne, they are reteyned: &amp; be thou a faithfull diſpenſour of the word of God, and of his holy Sacraments. In the name of the Father, &amp; of the ſonne, and of the holy Ghoſt. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. And then the Prelate delivereth to each of them, the Bible in his hand, ſaying, <hi>Take thou authority to preach the word of God, and to miniſter the holy Sacraments in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, where thou</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Note, how they may be made Prieſts, though yet they have no charge or flock to attend vnto.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhalt be ſo appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4135:19"/>Thus are they made Prieſts: &amp; when at any tyme they enter into a benefice, they muſt beſides have the Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Patrone (who may be a Papiſt or Familiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) &amp; the inſtitution of the Prelate, who is an Antichriſt, to whome now alſo they ſweare to yeeld Canonicall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; &amp; by whom otherwiſe they ſtand alway ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be ſilenced, ſuſpended, degraded, and deprived.</p>
                  <p>And for the works of their calling, ſome are ſuch as Chriſt hath not preſcribed to his Miniſters in his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſuch as be their ſolemnization of mariage, buriall of the dead, churching of women, reading of homilies, &amp; ſtinted prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) &amp; ſome being ſuch as Chriſt hath preſcribed, yet at they not ſo adminiſtred as he in his word hath ordeyned, but according as is appointed in their book of Common prayer, &amp; in their Canons, Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Advertiſements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to which they are bound to pray, and to adminiſter the word, Sacraments, and cenſures, among them.</p>
                  <p>Other particulars, many and ſtraunge, vſed in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance and performance of their Office of Prieſthood, I omit. Onely I will annex this one thing more, how by their Canons they have now provided further and made it a conſtitution of their Church,<note n="*" place="margin">Canons of Anno 1603. Can. 36.</note> † <hi>That no perſon ſhall be received into the Miniſtery, nor admitted to any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiasticall living, nor ſuffred to preach, except he be licenced by the Archbiſhop or Biſhop of the Dioces, &amp;c. and except he ſhall first ſubſcribe, That the book of Common prayer, and of ordering Biſhops, Priests and Deacons, conteyneth in it nothing contrarie to the word of God, and that it may lawfully ſo be vſed, &amp; that he himſelf will vſe the forme in the ſayd Book preſcribed in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick prayer, and administration of the Sacraments, &amp; none other.</hi> Alſo, <hi>That he alloweth the book of Articles of Religion agreed vpon by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of both Provinces, and the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4135:20"/>
whole Clergie in the convocation holden at London in the ye are,</hi> 1562. <hi>and that he acknowledgeth all &amp; every the Articles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned, to be agreeable to the word of God.</hi> In which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles although there be many truths, yet there are alſo errors not afew, to which they muſt ſubſcribe that they are agreeable to the word of God, and that they do thus ſubſcribe <hi>willingly and ex animo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, for their <hi>Biſhops &amp; Archbiſhops,</hi> 1. there is with other things aforeſaid, at their conſecration alſo to be read <hi>an Epistle, Goſpell, and Credo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. After which ended, the elected Biſhop muſt be preſented by two Biſhops, vnto the Archbiſhop of that Province, or to ſome other Biſhop appointed by his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the Biſhops that preſent him ſaying, <hi>Moſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, we preſent vnto you this godly and wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, to be conſecrated Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Then the Archbiſhop demaunds the Kings <hi>mandate,</hi> for the conſecration. And after a lawfull oth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Kings ſupremacy, they muſt take an vnlawfull oath of obedience to the Archbiſhop: which is thus, <hi>In the name of God, Amen. I N. choſen Biſhop of the Church and Sie of N. do profeſſe and promiſe all due reverence and obedience to the Archbiſhop and to the Metropoliticall Church of N. and to their ſucceſſours, ſo help me God, through Ieſus Christ.</hi> Which oath at the conſecration of an Archbiſhop is omitted.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Afterward vpon the Archbiſhops demaund he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth a number of queſtions, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Of <hi>his perſwaſion that he is truly called to this miniſtration according to the will of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the order of the Realme;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Of <hi>the ſufficiency of the Scriptures, and his determination with them to inſtruct the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to his charge;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Of <hi>his ſtudy faithfully to exerciſe himſelf in the ſayd Scriptures;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Of <hi>his readynes with all faithfull diligence to baniſh and drive a way all erroneous and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4135:20"/>
ſtrange doctrine, contrary to Gods word;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Of <hi>his care to deny all vngodlynes and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this world.</hi> 6. Of <hi>his purpoſe to maynteyne &amp; ſet forward quietnes, peace, and love among all men, and to correct and puniſh ſuch as be vnquiet, diſobedient, and criminous with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his dioces, according to ſuch authority as he hath by Gods word, and the ordinance of the Realme;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> Of <hi>his carefulnes to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf gentle, and mercifull for Chriſts ſake to poore people, and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> To all which they anſwer affirmatively, and walk for the moſt part negatively: as their eſtate &amp; practiſe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto all men, that will open their eyes to ſee it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Then muſt be ſung or ſayd, <hi>Come holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe direction given in the Scriptures for the offices &amp; ordinances appointed by Chriſt they reject, and follow the Papiſts and their owne deviſes, ſo making the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God of no effect through their traditions.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. For the conſecration it ſelf, the Archbiſhop and Biſhops preſent, muſt lay their hands vpon the head of the elected Biſhop, the Archbiſhop ſaying: <hi>Take the holy Ghoſt, and remember that thou ſtirr vp the grace of God, which is in thee, by impoſition of hands: for God hath not given vs the ſpirit of feare, but of power, and love, and ſobernes.</hi> Where note agayne their vayn preſumption &amp; impiety in taking vpon them to give the holy Ghoſt, having no power fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord therevnto. Yet I ſuppoſe this conſecrated Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop takes aſmuch as the Archbiſhop gives, &amp; the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop gives aſmuch as the Biſhop takes: which of what quantity and quality it is, let their eſtate and works be witneſſes.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Then the Archbiſhop delivereth him the Bible, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Give heed vnto reading, exhortation, and doctrine: Think vpon the things conteyned in this book: Be diligent in teaching and doing them, &amp;c. Be to the flock of Christ a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4135:21"/>
not a wolf, feed them, devour them not, &amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their practiſe is as contrary, as their office is degenerate from the ordinance of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And thus is their fourme of conſecrating Biſhops and Archbiſhops. Wherein I omit to note in particular their great abuſe and profanation of the Name and word of God, in the Scriptures and prayers then vſed, from the beginning to the end of that their conſecration. Neyther will I ſtand to ſpeak of their adminiſtration and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: nor of their other degrees &amp; functions of <hi>Deanes, Prebendaries, Chauncellors, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries, Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,</hi> and the reſt of that ſort among them: ſeing there are ſo many vnanſwerable treatiſes already publiſhed of this Argument, concerning the Antichriſtianity and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of their Offices, callings, works, and maintenance.</p>
                  <p>Yet before I end this poynt, I wil here ſet downe two of their owne late Canons, and ſome of the ſayings and teſtimonyes both of the Martyrs of old, and of the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Reformation in this latter age: that ſo their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition againſt the truth and amongſt themſelves may by this meanes yet further appeare.</p>
                  <p>Their Canons are theſe, 1.<note n="*" place="margin">Canons of Anno. 1603, Gen. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Whoſoever ſhall affirme, that the government of the Church of England, vnder his Maieſty by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, and the rest that bear office in the ſame, is Antichriſtian or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the word of God: let him be excommunicated</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>and ſo continue vntill he repent and publikly revoke ſuch his wicked errors.</hi> 2. And,<note n="‡" place="margin">Ibid. Can. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Whosoever ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme or teach, That the fourme and maner of making and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, conteyneth any thing in it, that is repugnant to the word of God, or that they who are made Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons in that forme are not lawfully made, nor ought to be accounted eyther by themſelves or by others, to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4135:21"/>
truly eyther Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, vntill they have ſome other calling to thoſe divine Offices: let him be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>not to be reſtored vntil he repent and publikly revoke ſuch his wicked errors.</hi> Theſe are their Canons, among many other the like, by which all may ſee how earneſtly they ſet themſelves to hold vp the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling apoſtaſie of the man of ſinne, as other before tyme have laboured to heale the deadly wound of the beaſt. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3-12. <hi>with Reve.</hi> 13.11.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The teſtimonies of <hi>the Martyrs</hi> to the contrary (which here I will mention) are theſe, being of ſuch alſo as were of our owne countrey. Iohn Claydon (burnt in Smithfeild at London, in the yeare, 1415.) held<note n="†" place="margin">Act. &amp; Monum. Edit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 5. pag. 588.</note> 
                     <hi>that Archbiſhops and Biſhops, ſpeaking indifferently, are the ſeats of the beast Antichriſt, when he ſitteth in them and reigneth above other people in the dark caves of errors &amp; hereſies.</hi> Sir Iohn Oldcaſtle, Lord Cobham (put to death about the yeare, 1417.) witneſſed,<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 518.</note> 
                     <hi>that the Biſhops, Prieſts, Prelates, and Monks, are the body of that great Antichriſt.</hi> And, <hi>that the poſſeſsions and Lordſhips of the Clergy, are the venime of Iudas ſhed into the Church.</hi> William Tindall (burnt by Filford Caſtell, in Braband) and Iohn Frith (burnt at London, in Smithfeild) pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed,<note n="*" place="margin">Tindals O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. And Practiſe of Prelates. Friths Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Antitheſis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Christ and the Pope.</note> 
                     <hi>that Archbiſhops, Lordbishops, Archdeacons, Deanes, Officials, Parſons, Vicars, and the reſt of that ſort, are the diſciples of Antichriſt, yea very Antichriſts themſelves.</hi> And Iohn Bale (an exile for the teſtimony of Ieſus)<note n="‡" place="margin">In his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of both Churches, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Rev. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and 17.3.</note> wrote, <hi>that the names of blaſphemie written vpon the Beasts head</hi> (Rev. 13. and 17.) <hi>are none other then the proud glittering titles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they garniſh their vſurped authority, to make it ſeem glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the world, having within them conteyned the myſterie of iniquitie. What other els</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>is Pope, Cardinall; Metropolitane, Primate, Archbiſhop, Dioceſan, Archdeacon,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4135:22"/>
Officiall, Chancelour, Commiſſary, Prebend, Parſon, Vicar, and ſuch like, but very names of blaſphemie? For offices they are not appointed by the holy Ghost, nor yet once mentioned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſayings of ſuch as of latter dayes have ſought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, which here I will note downe are theſe:<note n="†" place="margin">Admon, to the Parliam.</note> 
                     <hi>that the names and offices of Archbiſhops, Lordbiſhops, Chancelours, Archdeacons, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries, Officials, Deanes, Parſons, Vicars, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh prieſts, Stipendaries, &amp;c. are drawen out of the Popes ſhop as out of the Troiane horſes belly for the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods kingdome;</hi> That <hi>their Pontificall, whereby they conſecrate Biſhops, make Miniſters and Deacons, is nothing els but a thing word for word drawen out of the Popes pontificall, wherein he ſheweth himſelf to be Antichriſt moſt lively;</hi> That <hi>they enter not in by Christ, but by a Popiſh and vnlawfull vocation;</hi> That <hi>when they are made Miniſters, eyther they may tary in their Colledge and lead the lives of loytering loſels, or els go abroad with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Buls like to Circumcellions or Fryers to preach in other mens charges where they liſt, or els get benefices by frendſhip or money, or if all thoſe fayle, they may go vp and downe like beggers, &amp; fall to many follyes, or els (as many have done) ſet vp bils at Powles or at the Royall exchange &amp; ſuch like places, to ſee if they can hear of ſome good Maſters to enterteyne them to ſerve a cure.</hi> Thus have they ſpoken and written heretofore, when they ſeemed to loath theſe <hi>ſtinking abhominations</hi> (as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves then called them) and when they did not bring balme to cure the ſore of <hi>Babell,</hi> as now many of them do, though all in vayne: for ſhe cannot be healed, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.8.9. And hitherto of the firſt Argument, proving that the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblyes of England is the Miniſtery of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts apoſtaſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4135:22"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>THe Miniſterie of the Prelacy profeſſing it ſelf to be Chriſts,<note place="margin">II.</note> and yet ſtanding in ſuch eſtate as it doth not obey Ieſus Chriſt in his owne ordinance of Miniſterie worſhip and government of the Church, as their Prophet Prieſt and King, that Miniſterie whatſoever it profeſſe in word, yet is in deed the Miniſterie of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is the Miniſterie of the Prelacy profeſſing it ſelf to be Chriſts, &amp; yet ſtanding in ſuch eſtate as it doth not obey Ieſus Chriſt in his owne ordinance of Miniſterie worſhip and government of the Church, as their Prophet Prieſt and King.</item>
                     <item>Therefore the preſent miniſterie of the Church aſſemblies of Engl. whatſoever it profeſſe in word, yet is in deed the Miniſterie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>THe truth of the Propoſition is manifeſt: becauſe there is no other Miniſtery but Antichriſts that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in ſuch eſtate. And they are in deed of Antichriſt, that profeſſing the name of Chriſt, yet refuſe to obey him in his owne ordinance of Miniſtery worſhip and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, as their Prophet Prieſt and King. As may appeare by theſe Scriptures compared together, and others the like: <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1.2.3.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. <hi>and</hi> 17.5. <hi>and</hi> 28.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.27. <hi>and</hi> 22.25.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3-8. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.8.11.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1-4. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2.3. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.18.19.22. <hi>and</hi> 4.3. <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>Ioh. ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. <hi>and</hi> 14.9-12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
                  <p>The truth of the Aſſumption is evident, by that which hath bene ſaid in the Reaſons<note n="‖" place="margin">Pag. 2. &amp;c.</note> here going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And their conſtitution it ſelf ſheweth it, in that they are ſo farr from obeying Ieſus Chriſt in his owne or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Miniſtery worſhip and government of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4135:23"/>
Church, as they do all of them receive execute or ſtand ſubject vnto the Miniſterie and government of another Archbiſhop and Lordbiſhop then Ieſus Chriſt, of an Archeacon, and of a Parſon Vicar or Stipendary, being Prieſt or Deacon, ſo ordeyned by the Prelates: As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in their adminiſtration, reading prayers out of a book, ſtinted and impoſed vpon them, and obſerving many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inventions of men in the worſhip of God continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed among them: And likewiſe in their Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, according to their Canons, Courts, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, degradations, &amp; other like proceedings, by the Prelates and their Officers. Which were never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt, the Prophet Prieſt and King of the Church: as may be ſeen in his Teſtament, where they are not to be found. And this we have ſhewed hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more particularly in other Treatiſes already publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: to which I refer the Reader. <hi>Refut. of Mr. Giff. The Apologie against the Oxf. Doct. Treatiſe of Miniſt. of the Church of Engl. pag.</hi> 28.29.30. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>The third Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">III.</note>THe Miniſterie of Chriſtians which is oppoſed againſt and exalted above the holy things, Miniſterie, and ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt, that is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is the Miniſterie of Chriſtians oppoſed againſt and exalted above the holy things Miniſterie and ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>Therfore the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The firſt part of the Argument is certaine, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4. <hi>with</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.1.2.3. <hi>&amp; Rev.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The truth of the ſecond part of the Argument ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4135:23"/>
evidently: 1. In this, that a man may peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably adminiſter or receive their holy things, in their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by vertue of their Deaconry or Prieſthood received from the Prelates; which is the preſent Miniſterie of that Church, as hath bene ſhewed before. But if any do adminiſter or receive the holy things of God by the offices of Paſtors and Teachers, entred into and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to the teſtament of Chriſt, they are for this cauſe evil intreated, reviled, and perſecuted vnto death, even by theſe who profeſſe themſelves to be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. 2. Secondly, in that their Prelacy Prieſthood and Deaconry, is the very meanes of thruſting away &amp; kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of the Church, the Miniſtery and order which Chriſt hath appointed in his word.</p>
                  <p>Which ſome of themſelves have heretofore acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and written, affirming that <hi>Lord Biſhops, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Commiſſaries, Officials, and the rest,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Admon to the Parliam.</note> 
                     <hi>thruſt away moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegiouſly the order which Chriſt hath left in his Church, and which the Primitive Church hath vſed;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sermon on Rom. 12.</note> That <hi>they rob the Church of lawfull Paſtors, watchfull Elders, and carefull Deacons;</hi> And, that <hi>by the length of their vnlawful ſwords they keep out the lawfull members of the body of Christ, which is the Church.</hi> Neyther need we ſeek any further proof hereof, then that which is daily felt and ſeen, in their bloody oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and proud exaltation above the holy things, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt: Who being Lord over all, will bring their wayes vpon their owne heads, and when they have filled vp the meaſure of their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, will judge them according to their works.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>The fourth Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>THe Miniſterie which is ſuch as in the nature and condition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">IIII.</note>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4135:24"/>
of, it perteyneth not to any body and eſtate, eyther civill or eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but onely to the body and kingdome of Antichriſt, that is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Mininiſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is ſuch as in the nature and condition thereof it perteyneth not to any body or eſtate, eyther civill or eccleſiaſticall, but onely to the body and kingdome of Antichriſt:</item>
                     <item>Therefore the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſmblies of Engl. is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition none can deny. And for it, ſee 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>chap. with Rev.</hi> 13.11-18. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>and</hi> 16. <hi>and</hi> 17. <hi>and</hi> 18. <hi>and</hi> 19. <hi>and</hi> 21. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is cleare to all that will open their eyes to ſee the truth of it: in as much as their Prelacy, Prieſthood, &amp; Deaconry (the preſent Miniſtery of that Church) is ſuch in the nature and condition thereof, as the civill eſtate of the Common-wealth may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect without them: for they are eccleſiaſticall functions; the Church of Chriſt may be compleet without them, and yet have all the offices appointed by Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto; and the Turks and Pagans, neyther have them nor require them. Onely the body and kingdome of the Romiſh Antichriſt cannot be full and furniſhed in all the offices thereof without them. Which all men know to be true. From which alſo an argument to the ſame purpoſe may be framed in this ſort.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>The fift Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">V.</note>THe Miniſterie which is ſuch as the body of Antichriſt the man of ſinne cannot without it be compleet in all the members and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall functions thereof, that is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is ſuch, as the body of Antichriſt the man of ſinne cannot without it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleet in all the members and Canonicall functions thereof:</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4135:24"/>Therefore the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is cleare and certaine.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proved by the Canons, Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and eſtate of the Romiſh Antichriſt the man of ſinne, and by the conſtitution of that body in the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and functions thereof: As all muſt needs confeſſe, that have any knowledge of the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that Church and Officers perteyning therevnto.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>The ſixt Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>THe Miniſterie of Deacons Prieſts and Prelates,<note place="margin">VI.</note> which accounts it ſelf to be Chriſts, and yet in deed is ſuch as the Kings and Rulers of the earth may and ought to ſuppreſſe and root out of their dominions, that is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is the Miniſterie of Deacons Prieſts and Prelates, which accounts it ſelf to be Chriſts, and yet in deed is ſuch as the King may and ought to ſuppreſſe and roote out of his Dominions.</item>
                     <item>Therefore it is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is proved, 1. Becauſe there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch Miniſtery but Antichriſts, which accounts it ſelf to be Chriſts, when in deed it is ſuch as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ought to abandon and root out of their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 2. Becauſe that which is in truth the Miniſtery of Chriſt, no Princes may refuſe or ſet againſt: But in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſinne highly againſt the Lord, and provoke his judgements againſt themſelves &amp; their kingdomes. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12.13.14.16.17. <hi>with Pſal.</hi> 2.10.11 12. <hi>and Eſa.</hi> 60.10.11.12.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption hath two poynts to be conſidered: The one, that the Miniſtery of the Church of Engl. is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4135:25"/>
Miniſtery of Deacons Prieſts &amp; Prelates which accounts it ſelf to be Chriſts: which themſelves cannot nor will not deny. The other, that in deed it is ſuch as the King may and ought to ſuppreſſe and root out of his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Which we have ſhewed already both in<note n="†" place="margin">Treatiſe of Miniſt. of Engl. p. 25.105.134. Anſw. to Mr. Iacob. p. 163.197.199. The Apologie pag. 27.52.53.54.85. &amp;c.</note> other Treatiſes, and in the firſt Reaſon here before. And the forward preachers among them have yeelded it, in their ſuits to the Parliament to have it removed and taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And if the Prelates and their conforming Prieſts affirme the contrary, they are impugners of the Kings ſupremacy, and excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> by their owne Canons: the words whereof be theſe, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of their<note n="‖" place="margin">Canons of Anno 1603. Can. 2.</note> laſt Canons: Where firſt the Title is thus, <hi>Impugners of the Kings ſupremacy cenſured;</hi> And then the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelf followeth thus: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall affirme that the Kings Maiestie hath not the ſame authority in cauſes eccleſiaſticall that the godly Kings had amongst the Iewes, and Chriſtian Emperors in the Primitive Church, &amp;c. let him be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>and not reſtored but onely by the Archbiſhop after his repentance and publick revocation of thoſe his wicked errours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From which Canon, I reaſon thus: The godly Kings amongſt the Iewes had ſuch authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, as they might ſuppreſſe within their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions any Miniſteries not ordeyned by the Lord, and therefore any falſe Miniſteries whatſoever, as Ioſiah did <hi>the Chemarims, the Prieſts of Baall, them that burnt incenſe to the hoſt of heaven, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore alſo, ſeing the preſent Miniſtery of the Church of England<note n="*" place="margin">As hath ben proved before Pag. 2. &amp;c.</note> is not that which Chriſt ordeyned and gave to his Church, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently muſt needs be a falſe Miniſtery, the King of England having the ſame authority in cauſes eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call as thoſe Kings of Iudah had, may and ought to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and root out of his dominions this their Miniſtery
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4135:25"/>
and Prelacy of <hi>Archbiſhops, Lordbiſhops, Suffraganes, Prieſts, Deacons, Subdeacons, Archdeacons, &amp;c.</hi> Like as King Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eight did <hi>the Abbats, Monks, Nunnes, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And themſelves cannot deny, but eyther they muſt prove their Prelacy and inferiour Miniſtery aforeſayd to be ordeyned by Chriſt in his Teſtament, and ſo to be the true Miniſterie given by Chriſt to his Church, or els if they affirme that the King hath not authority to ſuppreſſe and take it away, they are by the ſentence of their owne Canons <hi>impugners of the Kings ſupremacy, and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>and not to be reſtored but after repentance and publik revocation of thoſe wicked errours.</hi> And ſo commeth vpon them that which Chriſt hath ſayd, <hi>Of thyne owne mouth will I iudge thee, ô evill ſervant. Luc.</hi> 19.22.</p>
                  <p>And wheras by the ſame Canon, the power of reſtoring ſuch is committed onely to <hi>the Archbiſhop,</hi> with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition aforeſaid, it would be knowen, if the Archbiſhop himſelf be in the ſame caſe, who ſhall now reſtore him; and whether it can be done to him any more then to the reſt, without <hi>his repentance and publick revocation of thoſe his wicked errours.</hi> Which if he and the reſt had grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, theſe queſtions would ſoon be at an end.</p>
                  <p>But howſoever they deale, and the Kings of the earth for a while mainteyne or ſuffer them, certaine it is that the King of Kings (the Lord Ieſus Chriſt) will in his time vtterly conſume and aboliſh that lawleſſe apoſtaſie and myſtery of iniquity in all the power and tyrannicall vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation thereof. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.7.7. <hi>with Rev.</hi> 14-20 <hi>chap.</hi> From whence we will take the next and laſt Argument, which now we will alledge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="argument">
                  <head>The ſeventh Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>IF the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies<note place="margin">VII.</note> of England be ſuch, as it ſhalbe aboliſhed by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4135:26"/>
the Lord, through the light and power of his Goſpell, according to that which is written, 2 <hi>Theſ. 2.3.8. with Rev. 14.6.7.8. and 18.4.5.20.</hi> then it is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie:</item>
                     <item>But the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is ſuch as it ſhalbe aboliſhed by the Lord, through the light and power of his Goſpell, according to that which is written, 2 <hi>Theſ. 2.3.8. with Rev 14.6.7.8. and 18.4.5.20.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Therefore it is the Miniſterie of Antichriſts apoſtaſie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is evident, as may appeare by the Scriptures mentioned in it.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption alſo is manifeſt, &amp; may thus be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: 1. The Scripture teacheth, that<note n="†" place="margin">2 Theſ. 8.3 8. with Eſa. 11.4. Rev. 14.6.7.8.</note> the Lord will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the man of ſinne with the breath of his mouth, in the power of his word; and therefore alſo his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit offices, ordinances, and authority. Of which ſort the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. being found to be, it will follow that theſe ſhall alſo with the reſt of that body be aboliſhed by Chriſt with the brightnes of his coming, &amp; with the breath of his mouth in the power of his Goſpell. Otherwiſe the man of ſinne ſhould not be conſumed away, as the Lord hath ſayd he ſhalbe; and hath therefore called him <hi>the ſonne of perdition</hi> or <hi>destruction,</hi> becauſe he is appointed to be conſumed &amp; aboliſhed. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. And ſeing that although in all other places of the earth, all the offices, parts, powers, and ordinances of his kingdome and religion were abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, yet ſo long as the preſent offices and functions of the Prelacy Prieſthood and Deaconry, in the <hi>Archbiſhops, Archdeacons, Lordbiſhops, Deanes, Prebendaries, Parſons, Vicars, and the reſt of that ſort,</hi> with their <hi>callings, works, maintenance, aſſemblies, Courts, Canons, and proceedings eccleſiasticall</hi> do continew in England; the Miniſtery power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the man of ſinne were not conſumed and aboliſhed, as the Scripture hath foretold ſhall come to paſſe; it muſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4135:26"/>
needs be that theſe alſo ſhall go into deſtruction with the reſt of that body. For true and ſtrong is he which hath ſayd it, and will performe it. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.1.2.8.20.21. <hi>and</hi> 19.1.2. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Agayne, ſeing the Scripture ſaith, that<note n="‖" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                     <hi>for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Sonne of God hath appeared, that he might looſe the works of the Divel:</hi> and the comming of the man of ſinne, in all his apoſtaſie, is in another Scripture ſaid to be <hi>by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Sathan,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.8.9. it followeth alſo herevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Chriſt the ſonne of God will break and aboliſh the Prelacy and lying Miniſtery of that lawleſſe one, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the reſt of his apoſtaſie whereſoever. Which already we have ſeen to be begun, in that the Lord hath now in this latter age of the world appeared (according to his promiſe) in the light of his Goſpell, and hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun thereby to diſſolve that work of Sathan, to caſt down Babylon that great city, to manifeſt and conſume that man of ſinne, to remove and aboliſh the offices, callings, works, and livings, belonging to that body and kingdom of darknes: So as in divers countreyes at this day, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Antichriſtian offices &amp; callings are generally rejected and abandoned: And in England, the Pope, Cardinals, Priors, Abbots, Monks, Fryers, and Nunnes, together with many of the popiſh hereſies, errors, &amp; ſuperſtitions are aboliſhed &amp; caſt out of the land. This hath the Son of God, that<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.8.10.</note> king of glory, by the ſhining brightnes and power of his Goſpell, already brought to paſſe in this latter age: Neyther will he ceaſe or give over this his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work; vntil he hath evidently conſumed the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of that man of ſinne, and diſcovered &amp; diſſolved the work of Sathan in Antichriſts kingdome throughout the world. <hi>The Lord of hoſts hath determined it, and who ſhall diſannull it? His hand is stretched out, and who ſhall turne it away?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4135:27"/>
Eſa.</hi> 14.27. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.7.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Moreover, the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyes of England being ſuch in their Offices, entrance, adminiſtration, and maintenance, as the Lord never ſet in his church (as<note n="†" place="margin">Reaſon 1.</note> before hath bene proved) therfore alſo it cannot be doubted but that theſe ſhalbe aboliſhed, as Chriſt hath ſayd, <hi>Every planting which my heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not planted, ſhalbe rooted vp. Mat.</hi> 15.13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Finally, the ſekers of reformation have bene (if ſtill they be not) of the ſame judgement and expectation. Els why have they ſued to the Parliaments, to have theſe parts &amp; remnants of the Popiſh Antichriſtian Kingdome yet reteyned in the land, to be removed and aboliſhed: yea and have expreſſely written,<note n="*" place="margin">Admon. to the Parliam. in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> 
                     <hi>that they ſhall downe, hold they never ſo hard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now furthermore that this deſtruction of Antichriſts kingdome and religion ſhalbe ſeen and done by Chriſts appearing in the light and power of his Goſpell, we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo from the Scriptures, which teach<note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 14.6.7.8. 2 Theſ. 2.8. with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa. 11.4.</note> that by the preaching of the Goſpell, Babylon falleth.</p>
                  <p>And for the better diſcerning hereof, thus we ſhew it further: Firſt, by <hi>Babylon</hi>
                     <note n="‡" place="margin">Rev. 17.5.7. with 11.8. 2 Theſ. 2.7.</note> myſtically and ſpiritually is vnderſtood, the city kingdome and iuriſdiction of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, with the offices and ordinances belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, the apoſtaſie and authority of the man of ſinne, the bloody and adulterous eſtate of the whore that ſitteth on many waters, with whome the Kings of the earth have committed fornication, and the inhabitants of the earth have bene made drunken with the wyne thereof. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>and</hi> 4.3. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.7.8.9.10.11.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. <hi>and</hi> 14.8.9. <hi>and</hi> 17. <hi>and</hi> 18. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the Lord Ieſus will deſtroy Babylon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4135:27"/>
the whoore, and conſume the man of ſinne, with the breath of his mouth, with the bright manifeſtation of his comming, and with the publiſhing of his Goſpell: wherein he will clearly and powerfully appeare, to the comfort of his Church, and deſtruction of the wicked. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.7.8. <hi>and</hi> 18.4.5.6.20. <hi>and</hi> 19.13.15. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>with Eſa.</hi> 11.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As God for a tyme hath ſuffred the Princes and States of the world to give over their power right and ſoveraignty vnto the Beaſt, to ſubmit vnto, authorize, and vphold the kingdome and juriſdiction of Antichriſt: ſo God agayne in his tyme doth and will ſtirre vp the Princes and Magiſtrates, to hate that harlot, to make her naked and deſolate of her honours, dignityes, and revenewes, to convert and employ her Lordſhips, lands, and livings to other vſes, and finally to ſuppreſſe and abandon her offices works &amp; abominations, which have ſo long deceived and defiled the world. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15.16.17. <hi>and</hi> 18. <hi>and</hi> 19. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly, this fall of Babylon, this conſumption of the man of ſinne, and deſolation of the great whore, ſhalbe performed by degrees: that as it roſe not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vp in a day, but firſt was in a myſterie, and then was revealed, and afterwards exalted: ſo it ſhall alſo decay &amp; be aboliſhed by little and little, till at length ſodenly in one day, even in an houre, this city and kingdome of Antichriſt be deſtroyed &amp; aboliſhed, ſo as it ſhal never be found any more: as when a great milſtone is caſt into the ſea and riſeth not agayne, and as of old it came to paſſe (<note n="†" place="margin">Ier. 51.61.62.63.64. with Rev. 18.20.21.</note> according to the word of the Prophet) in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of Chaldea</hi> which was a type and figure of this <hi>ſpiritual Babylon</hi> now ſpoken of. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.7.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8.9. <hi>and</hi> 18.2.7.8.20.21.22.23. <hi>with Eſa.</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>chap.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4135:28"/>
Ier.</hi> 50. <hi>and</hi> 51. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, at the overthrow and deſtruction of this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian kingdome and myſticall Babylon, her Kings, Marchants, Mariners, and crafteſmen ſhall mourne &amp; lament, becauſe of the judgement come vpon her, with whome they have lived in pleaſure before, and no man now buyeth their ware any more: but the ſervants of God ſhalbe glad and rejoyce, &amp; give glorie to the Lord, ſaying, <hi>Hallelu-iah, ſalvation and glory, and honour, &amp; power be to the Lord our God: for true and righteous are his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for he hath condemned the great whore, which did cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the earth with her fornication, and hath avenged the blood of his ſervants of from her hand. Reve.</hi> 18.9.10.11. <hi>&amp;c. with</hi> 19.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And hitherto of the firſt and ſecond Reaſon. Both which I have proſecuted more largely, as conteyning in them the ſpeciall grounds of this controverſie: namely, <hi>that their preſent Miniſtery is not according to the ordinance of Chriſt;</hi> and not this onely, but <hi>is alſo of the apoſtaſie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ.</hi> To which two heads, the other Reaſons here enſuing may be referred. Yet the propounding &amp; hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them apart from the other, ſerveth more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to meet with ſome objections, and more fully to inſiſt vpon other particulars, needfull in this cauſe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. And ſo we will now proceed to the Reaſons following.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:4135:28"/>
               <head>The third Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVHatſoever Miniſterie is ſuch, as none can heare it or have any ſpirituall communion with it, but in ſo doing he ſhall worſhip the Beaſts image (ſpoken of in the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation) and receive his mark in his forehead or hand: that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie may none hear or have any ſpirituall communion withall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the preſent Ministery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is ſuch as none can heare or have any ſpirituall communion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but in ſo doing he ſhall worſhip the Beaſts image, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his mark in his forehead or hand:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore none may heare or have any ſpirituall communion with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt part of the Reaſon is evident, becauſe whoſoever doth ſo worſhip or receive as there is ſayd, bringeth himſelf vnder the fierce wrath of God, as it is written, <hi>If any worſhip the Beaſt and his image, and receive his mark in his forehead or hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the wyne of the wrath of God, yea of the pure wyne which is poured into the cup of his wrath, and he ſhalbe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in fyer and brimſtone before the holy Angels and before the Lambe, and the ſmoke of their torment ſhall aſcend evermore, and they ſhall have no reſt day nor night, which worſhip the beaſt and his image, and whoſoever receiveth the print of his Name. Rev.</hi> 14.9.10.11.</p>
               <p>That the truth of the ſecond part of the Reaſon may better appeare, we are firſt to conſider what is meant by <hi>the Beaſt and his image</hi> here ſpoken of; what by the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4135:29"/>
                  <hi>worſhipping of it;</hi> and what by <hi>receiving his mark in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head or hand:</hi> and then to apply it to the preſent purpoſe. And firſt, that theſe and the like ſpeaches are not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken litterally, but in a myſticall and ſpirituall ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Spirit of God teacheth vs in playne words in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places of this book, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8.9. <hi>with chap.</hi> 17.5.15.18. <hi>and</hi> 11.8. <hi>and</hi> 1.20. beſides that it may be ſhewed by neceſſary collection alſo, as will appeare in that which followeth.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Beasts,</hi> the Scripture often figureth out men &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, of beaſtly qualities and conditions, ſo reſembling them for their fooliſh ignorance, ſavage cruelty, gredynes of prey, beaſtlynes of life, certainty of deſtruction, <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 7.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.20.21.22.23. <hi>with Ier.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.31.32. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12. And ſo here, by <hi>the beast &amp; his image,</hi> we may vnderſtand the Romane dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hierarchie reſembling it, the body of the man of ſin, with all the offices, functions, lawes, conſtitutions, power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority apperteyning therevnto. For which, compare this Scripture of <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.8.9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2.3. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18.22. <hi>and</hi> 4.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Ioh. ver.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. <hi>and</hi> 13.1.2.5.6.11.15.16.17. <hi>and</hi> 17.1.2.3.4.5.6.7. <hi>&amp;c. and</hi> 18.2. <hi>&amp;c. and</hi> 19.2.20.21. <hi>&amp;c. &amp;</hi> 20.4. And thus have the Martyrs of former ages alſo vnderſtood it, as may be ſeen in <hi>Act. &amp; Monum. edit.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 161 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <hi>worſhipping the Beaſts image,</hi> may be vnderſtood the yeelding of ſpirituall ſubjection homage &amp; obedience to that Antichriſtian kingdome, in the lawes, rules, offices, orders, power and juriſdiction thereof. And ſo this word <hi>worſhip,</hi> is much vſed in the Scripture. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.2.4. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 22.5.27. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 2.11. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.33-41. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 8.16. <hi>and</hi> 20.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.43. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18-23.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:4135:29"/>By <hi>receiving of the mark in the forehead or hand,</hi> may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the receiving of their ordinances &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions, to profeſſe or obſerve them, ſo as thereby we may be knowen vnto others (as by a mark in the forehead) or put in mynd our ſelves (as by a marke in the hand) that we apperteyne to that Romiſh or Antichriſtian king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And that <hi>the mark</hi> here ſpoken of may thus be vnderſtood, and not ſimply be taken for ſome viſible characters ſet vpon the forehead or hand, but even for ſuch accepting and keeping of the Beaſts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as is aforeſaid, appeareth plainely by like ſpeach and vſe of theſe phraſes in other Scriptures. As namely,</p>
               <p>For the one, that is the ſpeach of <hi>a mark in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> ſee <hi>Ezech</hi> 9.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.3. where the faithfull ſervants of God, are ſayd to be marked and ſealed in the foreheads; not that they received a viſible cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter or marke, but being ſuch as mourned for the abominations of others, and did themſelves conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and as it were with bold faces confeſſe Gods name and truth before the world (as the Apoſtle ſayd,<note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt</hi>) they were as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and certenly knowen by this, and in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the wicked preſerved by God, as if they had viſibly ben marked in their foreheads.</p>
               <p>In a like maner alſo, when one is not aſhamed of the Beaſts wayes, of Antichriſts ordinances and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but receiveth and profeſſeth them, having (as the Prophet ſayth)<note n="‖" place="margin">Ier. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>an whores forehead that will not be aſhamed,</hi> he may be ſayd to receive the Beaſts mark in his forehead, and be as plainly diſcerned of others, to be one of that body &amp; belonging to that kingdome, as if in his forehead there were a viſible mark imprinted.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:4135:30"/>The maner of ſpeach ſemeth to be borrowed from the common practiſe of men, who for ſuch things as they would have knowen and diſcerned, do vſe to mark them in ſome ſuch place as may well be ſeen and ſoone eſpied. So in <hi>the Paſſeover</hi> the lentill and doore cheeks (as being ready to the ſight) were ſprinkled with blood, that the Angel might ſee the blood, and ſo paſſe over the houſes that were ſprinkled therewith, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.22.23. Now in man, the forehead, or any thing therein is in moſt ſight and ſooneſt eſpyed: As when the leproſy ſprang in the forehead of <hi>Vzziah,</hi> as ſoon as the Prieſts looked vpon him, forthwith they perceived it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.19.20. And in this reſpect it ſeemeth the Lord commanded in the Law, that the plate whereon was graven as ſignets are graven, <hi>Holynes to the Lord,</hi> ſhould be alwayes on Aarons forehead, thereby to figure out the continuall mediation of Chriſt our high Prieſt, who appeareth in the ſight of God for vs. <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.36.37.38. <hi>with Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>and</hi> 9.24.</p>
               <p>For the other, that is, the ſpeach of <hi>a mark vpon the hand,</hi> ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.8-16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7-12. <hi>and</hi> 11.18. where Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſpeaking of the obſervation of the ordinances of the Paſſeover, ſayth vnto Iſrael, <hi>It ſhalbe a ſigne vnto thee vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thyne hand, and for a remembrance between thyne eyes, that the Law of the Lord may be in thy mouth: for by a ſtrong hand the Lord brought thee out of Aegypt. Exod.</hi> 13.8.9. And agayne he vſeth the ſame maner of ſpeach, towching the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ordinance of conſecrating their firſt borne to the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.16. And agayne, when he teacheth the Iſraelites continually to remember the words which God commanded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. By which Scriptures appeareth, firſt that by a ſigne on the hand is not meant a viſible ſigne or mark ſet or engraven vpon the hand, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4135:30"/>
(as Moſes expoundeth himſelf) the keeping of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and commandements of God, as <hi>the Paſſeover, the conſecrating of the firſt borne, &amp;c. Exod.</hi> 13.10.15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7.8.9.12. Secondly, that the keeping of thoſe ordinances as God appointed them, ſhould be as a ſigne vpon their hand to put them in remembrance continually of their deliverance out of Aegypt by the mighty power of God, and of their homage &amp; ſubjection due unto him for ever.</p>
               <p>Accordingly therefore by <hi>the Beasts mark,</hi> may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the keeping of his ordinances and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So as when men do keep and ſubmit vnto any the ordinances of Antichriſt, as his Miniſtery, Worſhip, Religion, a Courts, Canons or the like, it is as if they received a mark vpon their hand, to put them ſtill in mynd of their ſervice and ſubjection yeelded vnto him.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how the Scripture vſeth this maner of ſpeaking, when it would note the continual remembrance of a thing, as may be ſeen alſo by like ſpeaches in other places, <hi>Song.</hi> 8.6. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.16. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.24.</p>
               <p>And it ſeemeth (as the other) to be taken from the vſuall cuſtome of men, who becauſe the hand of a man is alwayes in his ſight, vſe therefore (when they would remember a matter) to put a ring or thread or ſuch like thing vpon their hand, that they may not forget but ſtil be put in mynd thereof. Such alſo is that ſpeach of God in the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>I have graven thee vpon my hand, thy walles are ever in my ſight, Eſa.</hi> 49.16. where the latter part of the ſentence expoundeth the former (a thing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vſed in the Prophets) and teacheth that in this place theſe words, <hi>to be graven on the hand,</hi> ſignify <hi>to be alwayes in ſight and remembrance.</hi> To which end may be obſerved, how the marke ſpoken of in the Revelation, is ſometimes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4135:31"/>
ſayd to be received<note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 13.16.</note> in the right hand, becauſe that hand is commonly the more vſed, &amp; ſo more often in the eye and ſight of a man, then the other hand is.</p>
               <p>And thus it appeareth, that they which keep the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and conſtitutions of Antichriſt, may juſtly be ſayd <hi>to receive his mark in their forehead or hand,</hi> ſo as ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they give notice to others, as by a mark in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, or be put in remembrance themſelves, as by a mark in the hand, that they apperteyne to his kingdome and juriſdiction. And this is the proper vſe of ſignes, marks, characters, and the like, by them to make difference &amp; diſtinction, to give knowledge vnto others, or to be put in mynd our ſelves, of ſuch things as we would have diſtinguiſhed knowen or remembred: as may be ſeene both in the continuall practiſe of men, and throughout the Scriptures. For which, ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.15. <hi>and</hi> 9.12.13.14.15.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.11. <hi>Num.</hi> 15.38.39.40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.38. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. <hi>and</hi> 22.15.16. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 2.18.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.5.6.7. <hi>Eſa. 30.</hi>17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.32.33. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>Moreover, that this is the meaning as hath bene ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may be gathered alſo by the contrary, which is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed therevnto by the Spirit of God in the ſame ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is, <hi>the keeping of the Commandements of God and ſaith of Ieſus. Rev.</hi> 14.9.12. <hi>and</hi> 20.4. For ſo in that place are oppoſed, on the one ſide<note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 14.9.</note> 
                  <hi>the worſhipping of the Beaſt and his image and receiving of his mark,</hi> and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 14.12.</note> 
                  <hi>the keeping of the commandements of God and the faith of Ieſus.</hi> As likewiſe in the ſecond commandement there are ſet oppoſite, on the one hand,<note n="‡" place="margin">Exod. 20.4.5.</note> the making &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing of any thing in the worſhip of God, or the ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to any ſuch inventions; and on the other hand,<note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 20.6.</note> the keeping of that onely in the worſhip of God which he himſelf hath commaunded. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4.5.6. Where
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4135:31"/>
alſo it may be obſerved, that the ſame words, of <hi>keeping the commandements of God,</hi> are vſed in both theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and<note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 20.4.5.6.</note> in the one oppoſed generally to all inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in religion whatſoever,<note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 14.9-12.</note> in the other ſpecially to the conſtitutions and abominations of the Romiſh and Antichriſtian iuriſdiction.</p>
               <p>As the faithfull therefore which in religion ſubmit themſelves onely to the truth &amp; ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of Ieſus Chriſt preſcribed in his word, are ſayd to keep the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God and faith of Ieſus, having this as a ſigne vpon their hand, and being ſealed therewith as with a mark on the forehead: ſo they which in religion ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to the ordinances &amp; conſtitutions of the Romiſh Antichriſt, are accounted by the holy Ghoſt to worſhip the Beaſts image and to receive his mark in their forehead or hand. And hitherto of the expoſition of this Scripture.</p>
               <p>Now to apply it to the matter in hand, it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2.3. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.1-6. Rev. 13. &amp; 17. chap. &amp;c.</note> firſt that this Antichriſt the man of ſinne hath made apoſtaſie from the ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he hath brought in and ſet vp in ſtead thereof his owne errors &amp; conſtitutions, the inventions &amp; works of Sathan: and particularly, that oppoſing and exalting himſelf againſt the kingdome of Chriſt, he hath turned the Miniſtery and government of Chriſt his officers (which be <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, and Elders</hi>) into the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and government of <hi>Archbiſhops, Lordbiſhops, Suffraganes, Chancelours, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries, Prieſts, Parſons, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, &amp;c.</hi> entring and executing their offices, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts ordinance, but after their owne <hi>orders, canons and conſtitutions.</hi> Thirdly, that notwithſtanding many popiſh enormities be already removed out of the land by the mercy of God, yet the preſent conſtitution
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4135:32"/>
of their Church-aſſemblies ſtill is ſuch as every one of them is ſubject to a provinciall Archbiſhop, to a dioceſan Lordbiſhop, to a Chancelour, to an Archdeacon, to a Prieſt, being the Parſon, Vicar, or ſtipendary Curate of the Pariſh: As alſo to a Book-worſhip deviſed by man, to the Prelates popiſh courts, ſuſpenſions, excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, abſolutions, conſecrations, orderings, degrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, deprivations, and other ſuch proceedings, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Canons and courſes: which in their order were erected and are reteyned in the Synagogues and kingdome of Antichriſt, but were never appointed by Chriſt for his Church and people to obſerve and yeeld vnto, as hath bene proved. Whereby it appeareth, that the publick Miniſtery of their aſſemblies now is ſuch as none can have ſpirituall communion therewith, but in ſo doing they obſerve and ſubmit vnto the ordinances of Antichriſt; and conſequently worſhip the Beaſts image and receive his mark in their forehead or hand, according as here before hath bene declared.</p>
               <p>Yet before I conclude this point, I would advertiſe the Reader, that ſome vnderſtand this <hi>receiving of the mark in the forehead or hand,</hi> to be meant of ſubmitting vnto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts ordinances eyther openly with a bold face, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly vnder hand. As alſo, that ſuch may be ſayd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the mark in their hand, which receive to execute any office or performe any work in the kingdome of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt by his power and hand, that is, by vertue of any authority received fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him or of any ſubjection yeelded vnto him. Which may well be applyed to <hi>the buying &amp; ſelling</hi> by vertue of the mark received, ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.17. But how ever it be for the propriety of the phraſe, yet herein do all theſe expoſitions agree, that thereby is vnderſtood the ſubmitting to Antichriſt his ordinances
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4135:32"/>
to be implyed, and therefore come all to one end as towching the matter in hand.</p>
               <p>And long ſince, <hi>Iohn Claydon</hi> ſpoken of before, a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr of Chriſt (burnt in the dayes of King Henry the fift, in the yeare, 1415.) held <hi>that the Biſhops licence for a man to preach the word of God, is the character of the Beast, that is Antichriſt. Act. and Monum. edit</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 588. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him agayne, Mr Ridley, another Martyr (burnt in Queen Maries dayes, in the yeare 1555.) writing largely of this matter to the Chriſtians then afflicted, ſheweth his judgement concerning it, thus:<note n="*" place="margin">Act. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. edit. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>1618.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Doth not Paul command to the Romanes, which perteyneth to every Chriſtian ſoule:</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> As you have in tymes paſt given your members to do ſervice vnto vncleannes and wickednes, from one wickednes to another: ſo now give your members to do ſervice vnto righteouſnes, that you may be ſanctified. <hi>And I pray thee good brother what doeſt thou think is to bear the mark of the Beaſt in the forehead and in the hand that Sainst Iohn ſpeaketh of? I know we ought warily to ſpeak of Gods myſteries which he ſhewed by the ſpirit of propheſying to his ſervant Iohn, yet to read them with reverence, and to pray for the ſame ſo much as God knoweth neceſſary for our time to know, I think it neceſſary and good. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what I ſuppoſe is to beare the Beaſts mark, I will tell thee, and commit the iudgement of my interpretation, as in all other things, to the ſpirituall man. I ſuppoſe he beareth the Beaſt of Babylons mark in his forehead, which is not aſhamed of the Beasts wayes, but will profeſſe them openly to ſet forth his maiſter the beaſt Abaddon. And likewiſe he beareth his mark in the hand, that will, and doth practiſe the works of the Beast with his power and hand. And likewiſe I will not let to tell thee, what I think to be ſigned in the forehead for the ſervant of God is, whereof Iohn alſo ſpeaketh, reckoning vp many thowſands ſo to have bene ſigned of every tribe: I ſuppoſe he is ſigned in the forehead, for the ſervant
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4135:33"/>
of God, whom God hath appointed of his infinite goodnes, &amp; hath given him grace &amp; strength, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stantly to confeſſe him, &amp; his truth before the world. And to have grace &amp; ſtrengh to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe Chriſt, &amp; the doctrine of the Croſſe, &amp; to lament &amp; mourne for the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Antichrist, I ſuppoſe is to be ſigned with</hi> Tau, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Ezekiel the Prophet doth ſpeak. Thus I ſuppoſe theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are ſpiritually to be vnderſtood: And to look for other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall marks to be ſeen in mens foreheads or in their hands, is nothing els but to look that there ſhould come ſome brute beaſt out of Babylon, or ſome Elephant, Leopard, Lyon, or Camell or ſome other ſuch monſtrous beast with ten hornes, that ſhould do all the wonderfull things ſpoken of in Iohn: And yet of a beaſt ſpeaketh Iohn: But I vnderstand him ſo to be called, not for that he ſhalbe any ſuch brute Beaſt, but for that he is and ſhalbe called the child of perdition, which for his cruelty and beaſtly maners, is called the beast. The carnall Iewes knew there was a promiſe made that Elias ſhould come before Christ the Meſsias (the annoynted of God) to prepare his wayes; they knew alſo there was a promiſe of Meſsias, that he ſhould come and be a King, and reigne in the houſe of David for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: But they vnderſtood all ſo groſſely and carnally, that they neyther knew Elias nor Meſsias when they came: for they loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for Elias to come downe from heaven in his own perſon, and for Meſsias to come and reigne in worldly pompe, power, riches, glory: whenas the prophecies of both were ſpiritually to have bene vnderſtood: Of Elias that he ſhould come, not in perſon, but in ſpirit, that is one that ſhould he indued with the ſpirit and gifts of grace of Elias, which was in deed Iohn Baptiſt, as Chriſt himſelf did declare to his Apoſtles: And of Meſſias reigne, all the Prophets were to be vnderſtood of the reigne of his ſpirituall kingdome over the houſe of Iacob and the true Iſraelites for evermore. And ſo by their groſſe and carnall vnderſtanding, they miſtook both Elias and the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4135:33"/>
true Meſſias, and when they came, knew neyther of them both. So likewiſe I feare me (nay it is certayne) the world that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the light of the ſpirit of God (for the world is not able to receive him, ſaith Iohn) neyther doth nor ſhall know the beaſt, nor his marks, though he rage cruelly and live never ſo beaſtly, and though his marked men be in number like the ſand of the ſea. The Lord therefore vouchſafe to open the eyes of the blynd with the light of grace, that they may ſee &amp; perceive and vnderſtand the words of God, after the mynd of his Spirit, Amen.</hi> Thus farre Mr Ridley.</p>
               <p>And Mr Bale (an exile of Chriſt) vnderſtanding by the Beaſt <hi>the great Antichriſt,</hi> and by his image <hi>thoſe gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours which take vpon them his blaſphemous titles, names, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or defence:</hi> applyed it alſo, thus,<note n="*" place="margin">Image of both Churches vpon Rev. <hi>14.9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>To receive the Beaſts mark in their foreheads and hands, is both to agree to ſuch decrees, traditions, lawes, conſtitutions, acts, and proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as they vnder thoſe titles have made, onely for their owne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſnes and pompe, and neyther for the glory of God, nor yet for the right maintenance of the Chriſtian common wealth: And alſo to be ſworne to the ſame, to ſubſcribe to it, to give counſel or ayde to it, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne it by learning, to minister in it, to execute vnder it, to accuſe, puniſh, &amp; put to death for it, or to think it lawfull and godly with ſuch like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I ſomewhat largely noted down the ſayings of theſe Martyrs of former times, as being of good weight to the matter in hand. For although Antichriſt was not then ſo fuly diſcovered nor ſo deeply wounded, as ſynce he hath ben and wilbe yet daily more in this latter age of the world (in which reſpect we are not now to be preſſed with every thing which they then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the darknes of Popery did receive and allow): Yet by theſe teſtimonies alledged and other the like in their ſtories, it may appeare how vprightly they jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and how faithfully they walked even vnto death, according to the meaſure of light reveiled
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4135:34"/>
vnto them: in which reſpect they will riſe vp in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to condemne this age, wherein notwithſtanding that Antichriſt be plainlyer manifeſted and more conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as yet ſtil he wilbe more &amp; more til he be aboliſhed,<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.7.8.</note> by the brightnes of Chriſts appearing in the light and power of his Goſpell: yet as if no ſuch thing were or ſhould be, or as if men<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 6.9.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.14.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.26.27.</note> had eyes and ſaw not, eares &amp; heard not, harts and vnderſtood not, who is there that do not ſtill take pleaſure in that vnrighteouſnes of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, diſobeying the truth of the Goſpell of Chriſt, &amp; worſhipping the image of the Beaſt, and receiving his mark in their forehead or hand? For which howſoever men do plead, yet let all remember and conſider, how the Spirit of God hath foretold the end and fruict therof to be this, to ſtand vnder the wrath and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, to be tormented before the holy Angels and before the Lambe for evermore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9.10.11. <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3-12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reason">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:4135:34"/>
               <head>The fourth Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>None may heare or ioyne in any ſpirituall communion with that Miniſterie which deriveth not their power and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Miniſtery from Christ, which is the head, for the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Church, which is his body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the preſent Ministery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. deriveth not their power &amp; functions of Ministery from Chriſt, which is the head, for the edification of the Church, which is his body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore none may heare or ioyne in any ſpirituall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Propoſition or firſt part of the Reaſon can not be denyed: 1. Becauſe none may be ſubject to any power or head in religion, ſave onely to Ieſus Chriſt, who is the alone head of the Church, in whome all fulnes of power dwelleth, and from whom alone the Church receiveth her life and ſtrength. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.22.23. <hi>and</hi> 4.8.11.12.15.16. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18.19. <hi>and</hi> 2.18.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.5.6.12.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Miniſters which derive not their power from this head to the execution of an office in his body, are vſurpers of that which perteyneth not vnto them, &amp; enemies of Chriſts ſoveraigne authority: and the people which heare them, or otherwiſe ſubmit to their power and Miniſtery, become guilty with them of treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of Kings the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.20. 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 12.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.12.13.14.27. <hi>with Exod.</hi> 20.4.5. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.4.9.10.11.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:4135:35"/>
17. <hi>and</hi> 18. <hi>and</hi> 19. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe God diſpoſeth the members every one of them in the body at his pleaſure, and hath fully fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his Church with all offices needfull: ſo as it is not in the power of any creature to give or take away any members to or from Chriſts body, or to approve by any practiſe ſuch giving or taking away vnder any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour whatſoever. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3-8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6.12.18.27.28. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.4-16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption or latter part of the Reaſon is proved not onely by this, That the Miniſters of the Church-aſſemblies of England have not thoſe offices and callings which Chriſt hath given to his Church for the work of his Miniſtery: as hath bene ſhewed before in the firſt Reaſon, to which this may be referred: but may alſo be made manifeſt further, and ſhewed by the contrary, after this maner:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of England, is of Deacons and Prieſts made by the Prelates, ſome of them being Curates, ſome Vicars, ſome Parſons, ſome Archdeacons, ſome Lordbiſhops, ſome Archbiſhops, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now theſe be ſuch offices as were left in England by the Pope, and are ſtill reteyned in the kingdome of Antichriſt: neyther were knowen in the Churches of Chriſt planted by the Apoſtles, but roſe vp with the body of Antichriſt, &amp; perteyne therevnto: as hath bene hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And, the Scripture teacheth plainly, that Sathan out of the bottomeles pit is the author and head of thoſe offices and functions which were formed and erected in the kingdome of Antichriſt the man of ſinne: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4135:35"/>
of the offices aforeſaid yet remayning in the Church of England. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.2.3.11.20. <hi>and</hi> 13.11. <hi>and</hi> 18.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.10.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And if Sathan be the erecter and head of theſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and functions, then it is certayne that Ieſus Chriſt is not. For what concord hath Chriſt with Sathan? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8.</p>
               <p>Wherevpon enſueth, that whoſoever adminiſter by vertue of the offices aforeſaid (as the Miniſters of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. do) they derive not their power and authority from Ieſus Chriſt the head of the Church, which is his body, even the fulnes of him that filleth all in all things: but from the dragon that old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, Sathan the head of the body &amp; kingdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the Prince of darknes, even the ſpirit that worketh in the children of diſobedience.</p>
               <p>And this have the ſeekers of reformation a long time ſynce vnderſtood, and publiſhed to the world: who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the eccleſiaſticall government of the Church of England, ſay it is<note n="*" place="margin">Admon. to the Parliam. ſect. <hi>14-20.</hi> T C first re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply pag. <hi>88.</hi> &amp; <hi>204.</hi> Mr. Fenners Anſwer to the Confut. of Nichols re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. pag <hi>61.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Antichristian and diveliſh and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Scriptures.</hi> That <hi>whatſoever commeth from the Pope (who is Antichrist) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth firſt from the Divell, and out of the bottomles pit:</hi> That <hi>the Names and Offices of Archbiſhops, Lordbiſhops, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries, Deanes, Prebendaries, Parſons, Vicars, Stipendaries, and Pariſh prieſts &amp;c. came from the Pope and are an Antichristian hierarchie:</hi> That <hi>Sathan is the authour of the falſe Miniſterie in the apoſtaſie of the Man of ſinne, and in the kingdome of Antichriſt the beast:</hi> That <hi>their offices and callings be ſuch as were firſt deviſed and ſtill are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the kingdome of Antichriſt, whereof they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but Sathan is the head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore let all men judge, whether any can with a good conſcience heare the word, receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4135:36"/>
or have any ſpirituall communion with their Miniſtery in this eſtate: yea though the men that be in it be of never ſo great gifts, and teach never ſo much truth. Is it diveliſh, and may the people of God joyne vnto it? Came it out of the bottomles pit, &amp; ſhall we ſerve the God of heaven by it? Do they which preach by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof, derive their power from another head then Ieſus Chriſt, even from Sathan the head of the falſe Church: and ſhall the members of Chriſt &amp; his Church, by hearing or otherwiſe, ſubmit their ſoules and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to be wrought vpon by it? God forbid. Know we not, that as the true Miniſtery was ordeyned by our Saviour Chriſt, for the edification of the Church &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the hearers: ſo the falſe Miniſtery hath ben e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by Sathan, and is reteyned by Antichriſt, for the ſubverſion of the Church, the deceiving and deſtruction of the hearers?</p>
               <p>We deny not, but many of theſe Miniſters be men of good gifts and preach much truth and comfortable doctrine: but this we ſay (and it is found too true) that the more gifts and truths they bring with them, the more they vphold this myſtery of iniquity &amp; Miniſtery of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than; the more deeply they inthrall the hearers vnder the bondage of Antichriſt; and the longer they deteyne them from the way and ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt. For who ſeeth not, that the dumbe Miniſters, though they have the ſame kind of Miniſtery among them as the reſt, even the ſame Deaconry and Prieſthood received of the Prelates (there being no other allowed in that Church) yet being of no gifts to call and intiſe them that paſſe by the way to come vnto them, are therefore much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and rejected of the beſt and moſt forward of the people? And would not the preachers alſo, who by their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4135:36"/>
gifts allure the paſſers by to come and heare them, be as much deſpiſed and rejected,<note place="margin">Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.13.14.15.16.17.</note> if they ſhould teach falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood onely, and no truth; impiety, and no godlynes? But how could they then ſo colourably entiſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayne their gueſts as now they do? how could then their ſtollen waters and hid bread be ſo ſweet &amp; pleaſant as now it is? how could they ſo greatly vphold this work of Sathan, and ſo long deteyne their hearers in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Antichriſts Miniſtery, and in defection from the way of Chriſt, as now they have done? So as all may ſee that by reaſon of the gifts they have and of the truth they teach, the abomination of their Miniſtery and Church-government is ſo coloured as few conſider it is<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> a myſtery of iniquity; few conceive it is<note n="‡" place="margin">Ibid. ver. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> the work of Sathan, few know that<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.18.</note> the dead are in their aſſemblies, and that their gueſts are in the depth of hell.</p>
               <p>And Sathan himſelf that ſubtill ſerpent and deceiver, perceiving how by falſehood onely he cannot continew thoſe offices and ordinances, which for deceiving of the world he hath framed &amp; ſet vp in the kingdome of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, is content for the vpholding of his work to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive many truths, to have the word preached, and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments adminiſtred, ſo as it be by his owne offices &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne ordinances (becauſe by this meanes his wayes and conſtitutions are reteyned) rather then by abandoning the truth vtterly, to have all his Miniſtery and works of iniquity diſcovered and quite aboliſhed. Neyther can we think otherwiſe, but he wil rather chooſe to maynteyne the ſtrength of his kingdome, in reteyning his officers and ordinances, though it be with loſſe of ſome falſe doctrine and admiſſion of ſome truths for a tyme, then otherwiſe by an vtter refuſall hereof to ſuffer loſſe of all his merchandize at once, not onely of his falſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4135:37"/>
doctrines, but of his falſe offices alſo and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by which he ruleth and adminiſtreth his Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian kingdome, and hopeth by them in tyme vpon fit opportunity agayne to bring in his former hereſies, &amp; to remove thoſe doctrines of truth, which for a ſeaſon he hath in a ſort ben forced to admit. He that can<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.14</note> tranſform himſelf into an Angel of light, can be content to yeeld ſomething for a tyme vnto the truth, that afterwards he may have the more advantage againſt it and them that profeſſe it. Therefore alſo it is no great thing, though<note n="‡" place="margin">Ibidem. ver. 15.</note> his Miniſters tranſforme themſelves, as though they were the Miniſters of righteouſnes, whoſe end ſhalbe according to their works.</p>
               <p>In the meane tyme, let none marveile if they ſee the eſtate of things in the world to be ſuch, as plainly bewray that Sathan and Antichriſt, ſo as they may have their Miniſtery reteyned, chuſe rather (when they cannot otherwiſe do withall) to have ſome truths of the Goſpell taught by their Officers therein, then to have both their Miniſtery refuſed, and every truth of the Goſpell freely taught by the Officers of Chriſt: thinking it to be better for them to continue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions with admiſſion of ſome truths, then that both Chriſts ordinances ſhould be received, and the whole truth yeelded vnto, in obedience of faith.</p>
               <p>But let all yet in the feare of God take heed vnto themſelves how vnder colour of learning the truth, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word, enjoying the Sacraments, and the like perſwaſions, they be drawen to have any ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with that Miniſtery aforeſaid, ſeing they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive not their Miniſteriall functions and authority from Chriſt the head of the Church, but from Sathan the Prince of the world; ſo as none can heare the word,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:4135:37"/>
receive the Sacraments, or learne the truth from their Miniſtery in this eſtate, but they ſhall therein ſubmit themſelves to that Miniſtery which Sathan hath ſet vp in the kingdome of Antichriſt, and continueth vnder theſe and the like pretences among his ſubjects. Fearful &amp; to be remembred alway is the verdict of the Apoſtle,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>that God wil ſend them the efficacie of deluſion that they ſhal beleeve lies &amp; be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe they beleeve not nor receive the love of the truth that they might be ſaved.</hi> And hitherto of this further declaration of the Aſſumption.</p>
               <p>Another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof is, that the Church-aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies of Engl. whervnto their Miniſtery belongeth, are not true viſible Churches of Chriſt, as now they ſtand. Therefore alſo it cannot be that the Miniſters thereof can in ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate derive their Miniſtery fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, for the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe Churches, as being his body wherof he is the head.</p>
               <p>That <hi>their Church-aſſemblies are not in their estate true vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Churches of Chriſt,</hi> hath often ben proved heretofore: and may be ſeen, in that they are vnſeparated from the world; not joyned together in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the Goſpel by voluntrrie profeſſion of the faith of Chriſt &amp; ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the government which he hath preſcribed to his Church; not having the power of Chriſts Churches, for the receiving of any truth, or redreſſing of any evil among them; but ſtanding in bondage vnder Antichriſt, in their Prelacy, Preiſthood, Worſhip, eccleſiaſtical Courts, Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Officers, proceedings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The further handling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may be had<note n="‡" place="margin">The Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to Oxf. Doctors pag. 44. &amp;c. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fut of M Giff. Anſw. to Mr. Stone, Mr Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Mr Hild. p. 62. &amp;c. Counterpoyſ. to Conſid. &amp; Argum. p. <hi>127.</hi> &amp;c.</note> in ſundry other Treatiſes; to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader: entreating all carefully to obſerve this here, that the Miniſters of the Church of Engl. not deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their functions of Miniſtery from Chriſt the head, for the edification of the Church which is his body, it muſt needs be vnlawfull for any, and ſpecially for the members of the body of Chriſt, to hear or otherwiſe to comunicate with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their worſhip, vnder any prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reason">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:4135:38"/>
               <head>The fift Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>NOne may heare or have any ſpiritual communion with thoſe Miniſters, which miniſter the holy things of God &amp; work vpon the conſciences of men by vertue of a falſe ſpiritual calling.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Ministers of the Church-aſſemblies of England, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the holy things of God and work vpon the conſciences of men by vertue of a falſe ſpiritual calling.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therfore none may heare or have any ſpirituall communion with the Ministers of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Major or firſt part of the Reaſon is proved:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the miniſtration of the holy things of God, is a ſpeciall part of Gods ſpiritual worſhip: and therfore neyther to be done by any falſe ſpirituall calling, nor to be received from any ſo miniſtring. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17.28. <hi>Epheſ. 4.</hi> 11.12. 1 <hi>Cor. 3.8.9. &amp; 4.1. &amp; 5.3.4.5. &amp; 11.23.</hi> 24. <hi>25. &amp; 12.4.5.6.13.18.28. 2 Cor. 5.19.20. Col. 4.17. 1 Tim. 3.15. and 6.13.—16. 2 Tim. 4.3.4.5. Heb. 5.4. with Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16.40. Ier. 23.16.21.22. Ezech. 43.8. &amp; 44.6.7.</hi> 8.<hi>9. Rev. 2.1.2.7. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the conſciences of the people of God are the Temples of the living God wherin he dwelleth by his Spirit, &amp; ought therfore only to be ſubiect to the Lord, and taught by him in his owne ordinance. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor. 6.16.17.18. with 5.20. Ioh. 13.20. Heb. 13.7.17. Rev. 22.16.17.18.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Lord Ieſus Chriſt alone muſt have this preeminence, &amp; the Church may not ſuffer any whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to beare rule over them at their owne pleaſure. <hi>Col. 1.18.19. and 2.18.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe in ſubmitting the ſoule to a falſe ſpirituall Miniſtery, men defile the Temple of God, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their ſubjection from Chriſt, and become the ſubjects of Antichriſts: as it is written, <hi>The Temple of God
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4135:38"/>
is holy, which ye are:</hi> And, <hi>No man can ſerve two maiſters: for eyther he ſhall hate the one and love the other, or els he ſhall leane to the one and deſpiſe the other.</hi> And, <hi>of whomſoever a man is overcome, even to the ſame is he in bondage.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. 17.18. <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>Cor. 6.</hi>16.17. <hi>with Mat. 6.</hi>24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.46. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom. 6.</hi> 16. 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2.3.4, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>The Minor or ſecond part of the reaſon is proved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they miniſter the holy things of God &amp; work vpon the conſciences of men by vertue of their Miniſtery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Prelates, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſpiritual authority, which is vſurped and Antichriſtian; and therfore by vertue of a falſe ſpirituall calling: as hath ben ſhewed before in the ſecond Reaſon, and is proved in<note n="*" place="margin">Mr Bradſh. Argum. 10. Mr Iacobs Reaſons for neceſſ. of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. p. 4.44.52. &amp;c.</note> divers of their owne writings. Yet here is ſomewhat to be annexed for the clearing of ſome exceptions, ſpecially concerning ſuch as are of greateſt forwardnes among them.</p>
               <p>Some there be which ſay, <hi>they preach not by vertue of their Miniſterie taken from the Prelates, but by vertue of ſome other cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and authority.</hi> Let ſuch conſider and anſwer, 1. Why they would ſeem to renounce that calling received of the Prelates? 2. Secondly, if they diſclayme that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery appointed by Law of the land, why they blame vs for doing the like? 3. Thirdly, if they preach by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of another calling then that they have received of the Prelates, how then they ſtand Miniſters of that Church where no other is allowed? and how they impoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vpon any of their pariſhes or aſſemblies, ſeing the lawes of the land allow onely the Prelacy Prieſthood &amp; Deaconry aforeſaid? 4. Fourthly, how they can avoyd, but needs they muſt be therein both intruders &amp; hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites? Intruders, becauſe they take vpon them &amp; exerciſe a publick office in that Church, againſt the publick lawes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:4135:39"/>
and conſtitutions thereof: Hypocrites, becauſe they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in ſhow one thing to the Prince, people, and State; and yet performe another thing in deed: They pretend and ſeem to ſtand by the Princes lawes, &amp; by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their calling had from the Prelates (for otherwiſe they could not ſtand Miniſters in any of thoſe aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies): and yet they practiſe the contrary, if they ſtand not by this, but by vertue of ſome other calling and authority, as ſometymes they affirme.</p>
               <p>But let vs ſuppoſe that which is not, namely, that they had ſome other calling which were lawfull: yet alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving or reteyning this vnlawful calling of the Prelates, this were but to halt between two opinions, and to ſet their threſholds by Gods threſholds, and their poſts by Gods poſts, even their inventions by Gods ordinances. Of which kind of worſhip the Scripture witneſſeth, that it is nothing els but <hi>to ſet a wall between God and them, and to defile his holy name with their abominations. Ezech.</hi> 43.8. <hi>with</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21.</p>
               <p>Finally, whatſoever they pretend of another calling, <note n="‡" place="margin">Mr Hild. to Mrs N. Mr Iacobs compariſon of mariage. His Reaſons for neceſſ. of reform. p. 50. Offer of Conf. pag. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>by their Churches or peoples chuſing, accepting, willing ſubiecting to their Miniſtery, &amp;c.</hi> yet it is evident that in very deed they preach the word &amp; miniſter the Sacraments, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute all duties of their Miniſtery, by vertue of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling taken from the Prelates: As may appeare by theſe reaſons following:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe they cannot ſtand publick Miniſters of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl., vnleſſe they receive of the Prelates the Deaconry &amp; Preiſthood aforeſaid. And at their ordination, they have this authority given them of the Prelates, when the Biſhop delivereth to every one of them, the Bible in his hand, ſaying,<note n="*" place="margin">Book of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering prieſts. fol. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Take thou autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to preach the word of God, and to miniſter the holy ſacraments
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:4135:39"/>
in the congregation, where thou ſhalt be ſo appointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe that alſo by the law of their Church, they are<note n="†" place="margin">Canons of Anno, 1603. Can. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>excommunicated ipſo facto, if they affirme, that they who are made Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons after their fourme of making and conſecrating them, are not lawfully made, nor to be accounted by themſelves or others, to be truely Biſhops, Priests, or Deacons, vntill they have ſome other calling to thoſe Offices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the people, even the beſt &amp; moſt religious among them (as now they ſtand in the confuſion and bondage of thoſe eccleſiaſticall aſſemblies, officers, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, &amp; proceedings) have not the liberty of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt, nor power in that eſtate to chooſe and ſubmit vnto the true and lawful Miniſtery appointed by Chriſt. Of which point ſee further, in the <hi>Treatiſe of the Ministery of the Church of Engl. p.</hi> 119.120.121.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, becauſe without &amp; againſt the peoples conſent (by whoſe approbation and ſubjection to their Miniſtery they would ſeem to ſtand) they are by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates alone, ſilenced, deprived, and degraded, from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing any Miniſtery in thoſe aſſemblies. Whereby even themſelves profeſſe to the world, that they have their Miniſtery from the Prelates; that they exerciſe it by vertue of their calling received from them; &amp; that they ſtill remayne in bondage vnder their Antichriſtian authority. Not to ſhew further in particulars, how their eſtate is ſuch (whatſoever they think or pretend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) as both themſelves, their Miniſtery, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtand all of them ſubiect to the Prelates, and to their Antichriſtian Courts, ſuſpenſions, exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and all other their proceedings, officers, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and conſtitutions eccleſiaſticall.</p>
               <p>In the Scriptures wee read, that the Apoſtles, being true Miniſters of Chriſt, would not at the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:4135:40"/>
and threatning of the lawfull Magiſtrates and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers leave of to preach in the Name of Ieſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.5.6.7.<hi>8. &amp;c.</hi> And why ſhould not theſe preachers, if they were in a true Miniſterie, much more refuſe to leave it at the appointment of the Prelates, who are vnlawfull v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers of the juriſdiction which they challenge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe in the Church? Yea if ſo be their offices and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority were lawfull, yet when they forbid that which God hath commanded, all the Scripture teacheth in ſuch caſes not to yeeld obedience vnto them any more then the Apoſtles did to the Rulers of Iſrael in the matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, <hi>that the Apoſtles had an immediate calling of Christ, and therefore refuſed to obey the Rulers:</hi> We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they had in deed an immediate calling of the Lord, but they made not this the ground of their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, neyther might ſo have done, if the Magiſtrate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement ſayd vpon them had ben lawfull. Here therfore two things are to be obſerved: Firſt, that in all lawfull things, the Apoſtles aſwell as any other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were bound to obey the Magiſtrates in the Lord. And ſo they both did themſelves, and taught others to do, ſaying, <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſoule,</hi> aſwell the Apoſtles and Prophets, as any other whoſoeuer. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13-17. Secondly, the Apoſtles being at that tyme ſo injoyned and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Governours of Iſrael, layd this for the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and ground of their anſwer and refuſall, <hi>that they ought to obey God rather then men. Act.</hi> 4.19. <hi>and Act.</hi> 5.29. Which is a duty as neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of all Miniſters and Chriſtians, as it was of the Apoſtles, <hi>namely,</hi> to obey God and not Man, when Man forbiddeth that which God commaundeth, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:4135:40"/>
that which God forbiddeth.</p>
               <p>An example in deed there is of Uriah the Prieſt, who at the commaundement of the King of Iudah made an altar after the faſhion of that of Damaſcus, and ſacrificed thereon. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 16.10.11. But therein he ſinned great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: notwithſtanding that he offered vpon that altar to the Lord, ſuch burnt-offerings, meat-offerings, &amp; peace-offerings, and at ſuch tymes of the morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice, as God himſelf had appointed. And if in that tyme of the Law he ought not to have done this though the King of Iudah commanded it, but ſhould rather have loſt his life for refuſing it: much leſſe may the Church-Miniſtery now vnder the Goſpell, at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of any Princes (Chriſtian or other) beframed or exerciſed after any new maner deviſed by Man, and leaſt of all after Antichriſts that Man of ſinne: Yea though in that Miniſtery many doctrines of the Goſpel be taught, and ſuch Sacraments adminiſtred as Chriſt hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For the other was but contrary to an ordinance given by Moſes, whereas this is contrary to an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance given by Ieſus Chriſt, who being the ſonne is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of more honour then Moſes the ſervant. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p>And here agayne concerning ſuch as plead, <hi>that they teach the truth and many excellent points of doctrine:</hi> It is to be obſerved, that yet none may therefore heare their Miniſtery vnder colour of learning the truth and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving comfort from them; neyther may for this cauſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſubjection to their Miniſtery and ordinances: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that although men heare much truth from them, yet in yeelding to heare &amp; receive it from Antichriſts Miniſtery, they defile the Temple of God in themſelves (if they be the Lords) even their ſoules and conſciences, and become the ſubjects of Antichriſt the ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:4135:41"/>
Not to ſpeak of the many errors and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, which they alſo teach and mainteyne. And for the truth which they preach, it is no new thing (as we have ſhewed before) that the Miniſters of Antichriſt ſhould in divers things teach and bring the truth with them. For when Sathan cannot by falſehood vtter his wares, merchandize, ordinances, Miniſtery, worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he will be glad to vtter the ſame by teaching the truth. He is beyond meaſure ſkilfull in framing deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and making them meet that they may be received: &amp; therefore when he perceiveth that he cannot get men to ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to his ordinances by hereſies &amp; falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, he yeeldeth himſelf to bring the truth with him, to the intent that his ordinances may thereby be received which otherwiſe would be rejected, and to the end they may be had in eſtimation and obyed even for the truths ſake which they bring with them. Of which thing ſee what is further ſpoken here before, in the other Reaſon, <hi>Pag.</hi> 66. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Mr Beza againſt Saravia hath a good ſaying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point, which he ſheweth by the practiſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles (ſpoken of in <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.24.25. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.34.35. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.16.17.18.) <choice>
                     <abbr>vidz,</abbr>
                     <expan>vide licet</expan>
                  </choice> that <hi>although Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ teach that which is moſt true, as ſometimes he doth, to the end he may vnder colour of the truth more eaſily ſeduce men to beleev his lyes, yet the truth is not to be heard and received from his month, but even then ought we to ſtop our eares, least vnder this pretence talking with him we be deceived by him: for the truth is not to be received from the ſpirit of lies and vntruth. And I would to God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that this were diligently obſerved of thoſe wiſe Mediatours, who think that compoſition and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be made with Antichriſt: ſeeking a mean there, where it is not at all to be found. Beza contra Sarav. cap.</hi> 25. <hi>p.</hi> 193.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:4135:41"/>Moreover, who knoweth not that Antichriſt and his Miniſters have bene and ſtill are in ſhow hypocriticall frends, but in deed great enemies of Ieſus Chriſt, even vnder the name of Chriſt fighting againſt Chriſt? Which thing how could they do, if they did not profeſſe and teach many truthes of the Goſpell of Chriſt? For if they ſhould deny every truth thereof, and ſay plainely that they were not the Church and Miniſters of Chriſt, then were they preſently eſpyed to be ſuch as they are; &amp; who would follow them any longer? But Babylon is<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev</hi> 17.5. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>a myſtery:</hi> and therefore not eaſily perceived or avoyded, till God reveale it and draw vs out of it. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will aright diſcerne the condition of Antichriſts apoſtaſie, muſt with <hi>Iohn</hi> be caried as into the wildernes in the ſpirit, that we may look vpon it, not according to the ſhow and account it hath in the world, but as it is in deed eſteemed of the Lord and diſcovered in his word. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3.4.5.6. And when it is ſhewed vnto vs, yet are we in our ſelves like <hi>Lot</hi> lingring and finding delayes, till God being mercifull vnto vs, take and draw vs as it were out of Sodom: whereas we ſhould be like mynded as <hi>David</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I have conſidered my wayes, and turned my feet into thy teſtimonies: I made haſt and delayed not, to keep thy commaundements. Pſal.</hi> 119.59.60. <hi>with Gen.</hi> 19.1-16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. <hi>and</hi> 18.4.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reason">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:4135:42"/>
               <head>The ſixt Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IF the preſent Ministery of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. be a straunge Miniſtery, then is it not lawfull in the worſhip of God to heare it or have any ſpirituall communion therewith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is a ſtraunge Ministery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therfore it is not lawfull in the worſhip of God to heare it or have any ſpirituall communion therewith.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The conſequence of the Propoſition is neceſſary, and cannot be denyed: 1. Becauſe Chriſt ſetteth it downe as a property of his ſheep to be obſerved, that they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not ſtraungers, but flee from them, for that they know not their voyce. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe he that miniſtreth in the Church being a ſtraunger, preſumptuouſly approcheth to miniſter before the Lord, and polluteth the Sanctuary and holy things of God. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. <hi>chap. and</hi> 18.4.5. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44.7. <hi>with Rev.</hi> 17.1.2. <hi>and</hi> 19.2.20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe by having ſpirituall communion with ſuch, we embrace the boſome of a ſtraunger, and ſo commit ſpirituall whoredome againſt the Lord. <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.20. <hi>with Num.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.39.</p>
               <p>The truth of the Aſſumption is manifeſt, if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what a ſtraunge Miniſtery is, namely, that which is not by the Lord ordeyned and given for that work: As ſome of themſelves have publiſhed heretofore, <hi>that the holy Scripture accounteth ſuch for ſtraungers in the Ministery, which have not their offices limited by the preſcript of Gods word:</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:4135:42"/>
And, <hi>it is all new which is ſtraunge, and ſtraunge which is not commaunded by the word of God. T.C. his</hi> 2. <hi>reply. pag.</hi> 438.439.</p>
               <p>And here before, we have proved<note n="*" place="margin">Reaſon. 1.</note> that their Miniſtery is not appointed by Chriſt in his word. Which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alſo have confeſſed and publiſhed, writing in an Admonition to the Parliament,<note n="‡" place="margin">Admon to the Parliam. treatiſe 2. ſection, 20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>that they have an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian hierarchie and popiſh ordering of Miniſters straunge from the word of God and the vſe of all well reformed Churches in the world.</hi> Where alſo they call all the Miniſters made by the Prelates (and others their Church hath none) by the name of <hi>New creatures.</hi> And in<note n="†" place="margin">Sermon on Rom. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> another treatiſe, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of divers of their chiefeſt offices, they write, <hi>that the Apoſtles never knew them, Sion hath not heard of them, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem which is above will not acknowledge them,</hi> that <hi>the watchmen being a ſleep, they crept into the city of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>have no title nor intereſt in the Church as publick members,</hi> but <hi>are rather members and parts of the strumpet &amp; whoore of Rome then of the pure virgin &amp; ſpouſe of the immaculate Lambe.</hi> Thus was their judgement heretofore: If now they be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe mynded, eyther they muſt ſhew out of the word of God, the offices, entrance, adminiſtration, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their Church-Miniſtery, or els (ſeing this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done) the ſheep of Chriſt muſt and will account them as ſtrangers, and therefore flee from them and the tents of their aſſemblies, leaſt otherwiſe they periſh in their ſinnes. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.5. <hi>with Numb.</hi> 16.26. <hi>and</hi> 18.7. <hi>&amp; Rev.</hi> 18.4.</p>
               <p>And to the end this thing may the better be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, let vs here a little conſider the hiſtory and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Corah Dathan &amp; Abiram,</hi> recorded in the book of Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. When God by the hand of Moſes had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Aaron &amp; his ſonnes to the office of the Prieſthood,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:4135:43"/>
Corah a Levite, and Dathan and Abiram of the tribe of Reuben, with other famous men of the Congregation, conſpire and ſtrive againſt Moſes and Aaron, touching the Prieſthood: challenging them that they took too much vpon them, becauſe (as they thought) the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood belonged not to Aaron and his ſonnes onely, as Moſes had appointed it, but ſeing all the Congregation was holy, and that the Lord was among them, therefore others of them alſo might have and execute it. Where further it is to be noted, that Corah, Dathan, Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, and the reſt, differed not from Moſes, neyther ſtrove with him in any point of Religion, but towching the Prieſthood and Miniſtery onely. They held that the true God onely was to be worſhipped; and not after any ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous maner, but according to his owne will, with the ſacrifices and the incenſe which he had appointed; and in all other points of Religion accounted fundamentall they agreed with Moſes. Onely in this they differed &amp; oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, concerning thoſe offices and Officers, by which the incenſe was to be offered, and other duties of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be performed, that is, as towching the Prieſts office: Moſes holding that the Prieſthood perteyned to Aaron and his ſonnes, Corah &amp; his company thinking otherwiſe. The matter is brought by Moſes before the Lord to be decided. He ended the controverſie, firſt by bringing deſtruction vpon Corah, Dathan, Abiram, and ſuch as abode in their tents; ſecondly by the bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Aarons rod and the not budding of the other rods of the Princes of Iſrael: and herevpon alſo giveth ſtrait charge, <hi>that no ſtraunger come neare to do the Priests office, or if any do come neare, that he dye for it Num.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>and</hi> 18.1-7.</p>
               <p>Now to apply this to the queſtion in hand, we may
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:4135:43"/>
thus conſider of it: That now the controverſie &amp; conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy being not againſt Moſes the ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but againſt Chriſt the ſonne; not about the perſons who are to be in the true offices, but about holding &amp; keeping in of falſe offices; not by Corah Dathan Abira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; others ſometymes viſible me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers &amp; famous men in the true Church, but by the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Antichriſt the great enemy of Ieſus Chriſt, yea by Antichriſt himſelf in his officers in the falſe Church: That therfore if the people then were bound to hearken vnto Moſes<note n="†" place="margin">Num. 16.25.26.</note> perſwading the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to depart from the tents of thoſe wicked men, and to touch nothing of theirs, leaſt they periſhed in their ſinnes, then it behooveth the people of God now to obey Ieſus Chriſt<note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> requiring vs to depart out of Babylon, and not to partake in her ſinnes, leaſt we receive alſo of her plagues: and therfore not to abide or have any ſpirituall communion within the tents, that is, vnder the juriſdiction &amp; in the conſpiracy of Antichriſt: yea not ſo much as to heare the word or receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, miniſtred in a true Church of Chriſt, by any officer of the kingdome of Antichriſt: ſuch as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſtery in queſtion hath been proved to be.</p>
               <p>For if at that time none of the children of Iſrael might execute the Prieſts office, being ſtrangers as touching it: then now may no Canaanite, no ſtranger, ſpecially by office, adminiſter before Ieſus Chriſt, nor be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Church: But all the veſſels brought before the Lord, muſt be holy vnto him: and therfore muſt be clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed firſt, and purged from the filthynes of Antichriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may be vſed in the houſe of the Lord of hoſts. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.40. <hi>with Ioel.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.21. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 35.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 52.11. <hi>and</hi> 66.20. <hi>with Heb.</hi> 3.1.2.3. <hi>and</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p>If any think, that yet notwithſtanding they may preſent their bodyes at theſe aſſemblies, ſo as they do not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:4135:44"/>
hearken nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent with the heart to that which is done among them, they both deceive themſelves and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with others, and (above all) ſinne againſt God, who in the ſecond commandement hath ſtraitly forbidden vs to ſubmit eyther body or ſoule to any ſtraunge wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or inventions of man in religion. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4.5. As accordingly the Prophets in the defection of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell taught the people, <hi>not to come to Gilgal, nor to go vp to Beth-aven,</hi> vnles they would multiply their tranſgreſſions. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Amos</hi> 4.4. <hi>and</hi> 5.15. And the Apoſtles like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have taught all Chriſtians what to do in ſuch caſes, <hi>Save your ſelves from this froward generation. Come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and ſeparate your ſelves, and touch no vncleane thing.</hi> And, <hi>Goe out of Babylon, that ye be not partakers in her ſinnes. Act.</hi> 2.40. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. Even as in the hiſtory of <hi>Corah Datha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Abiram &amp; the reſt</hi> hath ben ſeen, what heavie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came vpon ſuch as departed not from their tents but continued with them. Neyther wil it help to ſay, that they which were in that company of <hi>Corah and his compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> conſented with them in their conſpiracy; which theſe pretend they do not: For it is playne notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that when once they were warned to depart from their tents, ſuch as departed not, were deſtroyed in that deſtruction, all of them, even to the young children, who having not vnderſtanding, could not give conſent to that which was done. <hi>Num.</hi> 16.26.27.32. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neyther can the example of Naaman (ſometymes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged) warrant ſuch practiſe. For firſt it is manifeſt, that Naaman ſpake of two things, wherevnto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet giveth but one anſwer. The firſt, <hi>that there might be given him two miles load of the earth of Iſrael, becauſe he would thenceforth offer no burnt offring or ſacrifice vnto any other God, ſave vnto the Lord.</hi> The other, <hi>that the Lord would be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:4135:44"/>
vnto him, when his Maister went into the houſe of Rimmon to worſhip there, &amp; leaned on his hand, &amp; he bowed downe in the houſe of Rimmon; that when he bowed downe in the houſe of Rimmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Lord would be merciful to him in that matter.</hi> Which two things when Naaman had propounded, Eliſhaes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer vnto him was thus, <hi>Goe in peace.</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.17.18.19. Now whatſoever men would think of the latter of theſe, yet the firſt is ſuch as all will graunt to be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and vnlawfull: For there was no holynes in the earth it ſelf, and Ieruſalem onely was the place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſacrifice at that tyme. So as by the Prophets an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer (whether it were onely according to their woonted maner of bidding one another farewell, or to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; otherwiſe mynded, yet) there cannot be proved a conſent &amp; approbation given to the things ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>Next, let vs ſuppoſe that Naamans bowing down in the houſe of Rimmon, may have a double conſideration: one, as being a religious action; the other, as being civill. Religious, if Naaman himſelf worſhipped there. Civil, if the King onely worſhipped, and no other with him: ſo as Naaman now was with him but for to leane vpon there, as in other places at other tymes. Which being admitted, yet then if it be conſidered as a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous action in him, all know it to be vnlawful<note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 19.18. Rom. 11.4.</note> to bow the knee to Baal, &amp; therefore alſo to bow down in the houſe of Rimmon; and no more allowed by the Prophet, then his other purpoſe of having the earth of the land of Iſrael with him to ſacrifice vpon. And if it be conſidered onely as a civill action, then neyther were it to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in hand (which is concerning religious worſhip done or thought to be done by all preſent) nor for any perſons but ſuch as have like ſpeciall imployment about their Lords and Maiſters for vſe of their ſervice, when
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:4135:45"/>
they goe to the place of their worſhip. But now it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and playne that Naaman aſked pardon of God for it, and doubled this his requeſt for mercy, as being very much affected with it. Which for a good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing he needed not have done. And howſoever he purpoſed not hereafter to offer burnt offring or ſacrifice to any God ſave onely to the Lord God of Iſrael, yet he thought ſtill of bowing down w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> his Maſter in the houſe of Rimmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for which he craved mercy, as acknowledging it to be evill. And thus might the Prophets anſwer fitly and needfully be given vnto him, not as ſaying, <hi>Goe and do as thou hast ſaid,</hi> but, <hi>Goe in peace,</hi> trouble not thy ſelf with theſe things which would not further but hinder the peace of conſcience; &amp; being now clenſed of thy le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie be careful that thou ſinne not againſt the Lord, but ſerve him, which forgiveth thyne iniquity &amp; healeth thy infirmities: and peace from him be to thee. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.1.14.17.18.19. <hi>with Iohn.</hi> 5.5-14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.1.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 122.6.7.8. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.18.</p>
               <p>And otherwiſe, the approving of Naaman to come to worſhip in the houſe of Rimmon, ſhould both be againſt the whol courſe of the ſcriptures, &amp; againſt the practiſe of the Martyrs in all ages, &amp; a ready meanes for corrupting of others, and defiling himſelf, and diſhonouring the Lord whom now hereafter he intended onely to make burnt offring and ſacrifice vnto.</p>
               <p>And in this caſe we muſt alway remember, that as God hath made and redeemed both body and ſoule, and will glorify both in the life to come; ſo he will of vs be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this life both in our bodyes and ſoules, in all our wayes, and ſpecially in the ſervice and worſhip of his Name. Therfore would not the ſeven thowſand in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs tyme bow the knee vnto Baall, nor kiſſe him with their mouth. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.18. Therefore would not Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:4135:45"/>
Meſhach, and Abednego, fall downe and bow themſelves to the image that King Nebuchadnezar had ſet vp: And when he threatned them &amp; ſayd, <hi>If ye bow not down, ye ſhalbe cast immediatly into the mids of an hote fiery for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace: for who is that God, that can deliver you out of my hands?</hi> they anſwered and ſayd to the King, <hi>O Nebuchadnezar, wee are not carefull concerning this matter to anſwer thee: Whether it be that our God whom we ſerve, who is able to deliver vs, do fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hote fiery fornace &amp; from thyne hand, ô King, deliver vs: Or whether he do not, be it knowen to thee ô King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor bow down to the golden image, which thou haſt ſet vp. Dan.</hi> 3.12-18.</p>
               <p>The like work of faith ſhould be ſeen in all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. For<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10.</note> 
                  <hi>with the hart man beleeveth vnto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and with the mouth man confeſſeth to ſalvation.</hi> And our bodies are not our owne any more then our ſoules, but both of them are the Lords, who hath <hi>bought them with a price.</hi> Therefore ought we to glorify God in both, and to yeeld the one no more then the other to any falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or vncleannes whatſoever. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.20.</p>
               <p>Finally, it ſhould els be lawful to preſent our bodies at the Maſſe, and at any idolatry old or new whereſoever. And how then have ther ben or can ther ever be any Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Ieſus, which are on his ſide, called and choſen and faithful? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.6.14. <hi>and</hi> 19.11.14. <hi>and</hi> 20.4.</p>
               <p>But to leave ſuch vnconſcionable diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blers to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, let not vs forget that the Lord our God hath forbidden vs to endow any other, to receive or bow down to any inventions of Man in religion, ſpecially to the conſtitutions and worſhip of Antichriſt. And let vs take heed we provoke not the Lord to anger, who is a je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, not enduring that his people ſhould imbrace the boſome of a ſtranger and break his covenant, but pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:4135:46"/>
forth his wrath for this cauſe vpon his people, &amp; viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this iniquity even vpon the third and fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them that hate him, and keep not his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but go a whoring with their owne inventions. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4.5.6. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.39. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.4. <hi>and</hi> 106.35-40. <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9.10.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.4.5. <hi>and</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="reason">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:4135:46"/>
               <head>The ſeventh Reaſon.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IF the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. be not from heaven, but of men: then is it not lawfull in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God to heare it or have any ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion therewith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of Engl. is not from heaven, but of men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore it is not lawfull in the worſhip of God to heare it or have any ſpirituall communion therewith.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The conſequence of the Propoſition is manifeſt:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Miniſterie with which we may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communicate is from heaven, that is, appointed by God and warranted in his word. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25.26. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.8.11.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the worſhipping of God by a Miniſterie framed by Man, is a breach of the ſecond commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which the Lord hath threatned ſeverely to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30.31.32. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29.13. <hi>with Mat.</hi> 15.15.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe ſuch a miniſtery is vncleane and lothſome in Gods ſight, ſo as the people of God can have no ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified vſe thereof. <hi>Num.</hi> 15.39.40. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.9. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.22. <hi>and</hi> 52.11. <hi>and</hi> 66.20. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4.</p>
               <p>The truth of the Aſſumption is evident: becauſe God hath not appointed the Miniſtery of the Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Engl. but Man hath framed and ſet it vp. Which may plainely be ſeen by comparing the Book of God, &amp; their Books together: The <hi>Book of God,</hi> where their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces callings and adminiſtration cannot be found to be
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:4135:47"/>
from heaven, ordeyned by the Lord: Their owne <hi>Books of making and conſecrating Biſhops Prieſts and Deacons;</hi> of <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer and administration of the ſacraments;</hi> of <hi>Canons and conſtitutions, &amp;c.</hi> where they are readily found to be of Men, erected and authoriſed by themſelves.</p>
               <p>If any wil yet ſay, their callings &amp; functions are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let them ſhew it out of the word of God. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew (I ſay) that Chriſt the Lord hath ordeyned their offices, entrance, and adminiſtration: Their <hi>Offices</hi> of Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Lordbiſhops, Suffraganes, Cathedrall and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Deanes, Prebendaries, Archdeacons, Subdeacons, Parſons, Vicars, Curates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their <hi>Entrance</hi> by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, by whom they are made Deacons and Prieſts and conſecrated Biſhops, according to their book of ordering and conſecration; as alſo, their preſentation to benefices by the Patrones, &amp; inſtitution by the Prelates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of the word, prayer, Sacraments, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, according to their Conſtitutions, book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, Injunctions, Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For this is the way, &amp; this only, to warrant their eſtate, &amp; ſtabliſh the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſuch as are troubled about it. Yet this they doe not, but partly by cavils and exceptions againſt the truth and witneſſes of it, partly by vaine pretences of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and humane authority, partly by abuſe and falſe gloſes of Scripture, partly by reproches and perſecutions of all ſorts, ſet themſelves to obſcure the light of the truth now manifeſted, and to turne away the people from the knowledge and obedience thereof.</p>
               <p>Which is the more lamentable, conſidering what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them have judged and written of theſe things themſelves. One thus,<note n="*" place="margin">T. C. first reply. p. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>The Miniſterie of the Goſpell, and the functions there of ought to be from heaven &amp; of God, &amp; not invented by the brayne of men. From heaven (I ſay) and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:4135:47"/>
becauſe although it be executed by earthly men, and the Ministers alſo are choſen by men like vnto themſelves, yet becauſe it is done by the word and inſtitution of God that hath</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Note this.</note> 
                  <hi>not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordeyned that the word ſhould be preached, but hath ordeyned alſo in what order and by whom it ſhould be preached, it may well be accounted to come from heaven and from God. Seing therefore that theſe functions of the Archbiſhop and Archdeacon are not in the word of God, it followeth that they are of the earth, and ſo can do no good, but much harme in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another thus,<note n="‖" place="margin">Demonſtr. of Diſcipl. in the Preface to the Reader.</note> 
                  <hi>Albeit many nations that have renounced that whore of Rome, are heynouſly ſinful against the glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty of Ieſus Chriſt; yet is there none in the whole world ſo far out of ſquare as England in reteyning that popiſh hierarchie, first coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the midſt of the mysterie of iniquity, and that filthy ſink of the Canon Law, which was invented &amp; patched together, for the confirming and increaſing of the kingdome of Antichrist: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as great indignity is offered vnto Ieſus Christ, in committing his Church vnto the government of the ſame, as can be, by meane vnderlings vnto a King; in committing his beloved ſpouſe vnto the direction of the miſtreſſe of the Stewes, and inforcing her to live after the orders of a brothelhouſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third thus,<note n="*" place="margin">Removall of Imputations laid vpon the Minist. of Devon: and Cornwall. pag. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It is a matter which by all the straynings of men therein employed, could never yet be cleared,</hi> that Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and Dioceſan Biſhops are by Divine Right, rather then by Humane Pollicie. <hi>We for our parts hold theſe things firme: Firſt, that that Church-calling for which the ſcripture gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth no expreſſe warrant, is meerly vſurped and vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. The office of Iohn (though it were extraordinary) yet we ſee the care of the holy Ghoſt, to prove it by the Scripture,</hi>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> This is he of whom it is ſpoken by the Prophet Eſaias. <hi>Let any divine tell me what doctrine he would collect, if he were to preach vpon that place. Secondly, that the Holy writt makes no mention of any ſuch B. as is now amongſt vs. Shew
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:4135:48"/>
me (who can) the title</hi> Epiſcopus <hi>or</hi> Biſhop <hi>given there to any mortall men in reſpect of other Paſtors, and not wholy and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in reſpect of the flock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And divers others of them thus,<note n="†" place="margin">Admon. 1. and 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Not onely the office of Elders but their name alſo is out of this Engliſh Church vtterly removed, and in stead of them in every Church the Pope hath brought in and they in England yet mainteyne the Lordſhip of one man over many Churches. Which Lordbiſhops being not able (as the Elders) to execute their offices in their owne perſons without ſubſtitutes, have therefore their vnder officers, as Suffraganes, Chancelours, Archdeacons, Officials, Commiſſaries, and ſuch like.</hi> Alſo, <hi>They with their Canons and Courts are drawen out of the Popes ſhop, &amp; take vpon them (which is most horrible) the rule of Gods Church, thruſting away moſt ſacrilegiouſly that order which Christ hath left in his Church and which the Primitive Church hath vſed, yea robbing the Church of lawful Pastors, Elders, and Deacons.</hi> And, <hi>In a few words to ſpeak what we meane, Eyther muſt we have a right ministery of God, &amp; a right govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church, according to the Scriptures ſet vp (both which we lack) or els there can be no right Religion, nor yet for contempt thereof can Gods plagues be from vs any while deferred.</hi> Thus &amp; much more have ſundry of themſelves written in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tymes, how ever it be that now they would ſeem to plead otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>But to let them alone, by this may appeare how need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is for all, both Miniſters and people, to take heed to their wayes, and to lay them to heart. Towching the Miniſters, it ſhould herein be with them, as it was with <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> who proved his calling by the word to be from heaven, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.22.23. <hi>with Mat.</hi> 21.25. And they that are in deed true Miniſters, will have ſpeciall care and alway be able to ſhew their offices and callings to be of the Lord, from heaven, approved by his word. So
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:4135:48"/>
were the Prieſts and Prophets in the tyme of the Law: So were alſo the Apoſtles and Miniſters of the Primitive Churches vnder the Goſpell: Yea &amp; Chriſt himſelf like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And if we may certainely affirme, that the Chriſt who cannot approve his calling by the Scripture is not the true Chriſt, but a falſe Chriſt, and therefore to be avoyded, notwithſtanding any truth he profeſſeth and publiſheth: then may we as ſurely conclude, that the Miniſters which cannot prove their callings by the word of God are falſe Miniſters, and therefore not to be joyned withall, whatſoever truth they teach or bring with them otherwiſe. And if the Prophets, Apoſtles, Iohn Baptiſt; &amp; Chriſt himſelf would not take this honour vnto them, to be priviledged from having and ſhewing warrant of their callings out of the word of God: who and what are the Miniſters of the Church of England, that they ſhould be exempt from this ſo equall, ſo needfull, ſo generall a condition? And if they be not exempt, why are they not ready and carefull to ſhew it, for the ſatiſfying of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and defence of themſelves?</p>
               <p>And for the people (howſoever the Miniſters do) it ſhould be with them, as it was with the children of Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben and the children of Gad and half tribe of Manaſſes, who ſayd, <hi>God forbid, that we ſhould rebell againſt the Lord, &amp; turne away this day from the Lord to build an altar for burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring, for meat offring, or for ſacrifice, ſave the altar of the Lord our God, that is before his tabernacle. Ioſh.</hi> 22.29. So ſhould all Chriſtians be likewiſe mynded and ſay, Far be it from vs, that we ſhould rebell againſt the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; turne this day from him, in appointing for our ſelves (or ſubmitting our ſelves vnto) any office or calling, for the adminiſtration of the word, prayer, or Sacraments, ſave onely that Miniſtery which Chriſt our Saviour hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in his word. Of which ſort becauſe theſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:4135:49"/>
of the Church of England are not, far be it that we ſhould rebell againſt the Lord our God, and turne away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in receiving of them, in mainteyning or ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves vnto them, by hearing of them or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with them in their Miniſtery any other wayes.</p>
               <p>If it be ſayd, that all that theſe Miniſters do, is to the Lord; and that the things which they do are ſuch as he hath commaunded, as reading the Scriptures, teaching the truth, praying, baptizing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet this doth not help them, nor covereth their ſinne. For beſides that which hath ben ſpoken before concerning this poynt, we may ſee here by this example, how the Reubenites and the reſt confeſſed, that although they had built their Altar for the true God, and to ſerve him by no other ſacrifices then he required, yet their attempt therein ſhould not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be rebellion againſt the Lord, and apoſtaſie from their God. The ſame likewiſe is to be mynded for all falſe Miniſteries &amp; deviſes of men in the worſhip of God vnder the Goſpel. For whatſoever things ar writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aforetyme, they are afore-written for our learning and inſtruction. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. And hitherto of theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Now the God of all grace give vs to agree and be like mynded in the truth and ſyncerity of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt: that wee may ſet our hearts to receive &amp; keep whatſoever the Lord hath commanded, and in one accord with one mouth may praiſe God even the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: To whom be glory and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for ever &amp; ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:49"/>
            <head>OTHER ARGVMENTS and Reaſons, taken out of divers Books, old and new, written by the forward Preachers concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ceremonies, Miniſtery, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of England:</head>
            <p>Tending to the ſame end and proving the ſame thing with the Reaſons here before alledged, <choice>
                  <abbr>vidz,</abbr>
                  <expan>vide licet</expan>
               </choice> That it is notlawfull to heare or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of England.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>The firſt Argument, taken out of Mr W. Br. Twelve Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made by him againſt their Ceremonies; and thus applyed vnto their Miniſtery.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ALl Wil. worſhip is ſinne:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To heare or communicate with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England, in Church Service in maner and forme preſcribed, is a Wil-worſhip.</hi> Ergo</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To heare or communicate with that Ministerie is ſinne.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Propoſition cannot be denied, for the Apoſtle Paul plainely condemneth Wil worſhip.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption may thus be proved:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All pars of Divine Service and Worſhip, impoſed onely by the will and pleaſure of Man, vpon the communicants in Divine
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:4135:50"/>
Service, and that of neceſsity to be done, is Wil-worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to heare or communicate with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of England, in Church Service in maner &amp; forme preſcribed, is 1. a part of Divine Service and Worſhip, 2. impoſed onely by the pleaſure &amp; will of Men, vpon the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants in Divine Service,</hi> 3. <hi>of neceſſity to be done therin.</hi> Ergo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To heare or communicate with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church. aſſemblies of England in maner and forme preſcribed, is a Wil-worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Propoſition is as cleare as the Sunne at noone day.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption hath three parts:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is, <hi>That to heare or communicate with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Ministerie of the Church of England, &amp;c. is a part of Divine worſhip and Service.</hi> Which cannot be denyed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond part of the Aſſumption is: <hi>That it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed onely vpon the pleaſure and will of man.</hi> Which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſeing Man impoſeth it vpon man, &amp; God hath not in his word appointed their Offices callings and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, neyther required any to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with them in Church ſervice, in maner and forme preſcribed. Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which, beſides that we have ſpoken in the former Reaſons, ſee in their owne books what themſelves have publiſhed: a proof whereof in ſundry particulars we have given both heretofore, and in this preſent Treatiſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third part of the Aſſumption is: <hi>That it is of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity to be done in Divine Service.</hi> Which is alſo out of all doubt: For the people ſtand bound to heare &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with them, vpon payne of ſuſpenſion, exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, paying twenty pound a moneth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and God muſt have no ſolemne Worſhip in England, except it be in communion with the ſame.</p>
               <p>Vpon all this it followes, <hi>That to heare and communicate with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England in maner &amp; forme preſcribed, is to do that which is a part of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip impoſed onely by the will of Man, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:4135:50"/>
               <head>The ſecond Argument, taken out of the ſame Treatiſe.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>IT is a ſinne againſt God for Christians to partake with the Miniſterie of ſuch, as accounting themſelves to be ſervants of Ieſus Christ, yet do in the execution of their Miniſtery, give ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Honour to Antichrist and his Officers.</item>
                  <item>But the Ministerie of the Church of England is ſuch, as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters account themſelves to be ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt, and yet in the execution of their Ministerie, give ſpeciall Honour to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist and his Officers. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>It is a ſinne against God for Christians to partake with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the Church of England.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Propoſition is manifeſt and cleare to any that have an eye of Reaſon and any light of Divinity ſhining in it. For which ſee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14-17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption hath two parts; Firſt, <hi>that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Church of England, account themſelves to be ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Which themſelves will freely graunt. For here they ſay, that <hi>by way of Excellency</hi> they are ſo.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, <hi>that they do in the execution of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, give ſpeciall honour to Antichrist &amp; his Officers.</hi> Which is proved (If our adverſaries will graunt, that the Pope is Antichriſt, and the Prelates Antichriſtian officers) by this reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such a conformity to Antichriſt and his Officers in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, as is not onely beſides the word of God, but in a ſpecial ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner derogatorie to all reformed Churches that have depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Synagogue of Rome, is a ſpeciall honour to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ and his Officers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:4135:51"/>But the execution of the Miniſtery of the Church of England, is ſuch a conformity to Antichrist and his Officers. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The execuion of that Miniſterie, in the manner aforeſaid, is to give ſpeciall honour to Antichrist and his Officers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Propoſition is without exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Aſſumption is thus proved:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To execute a Ministerie vnder Antichriſts Hierarchie, and that alſo by vertue of a calling received according to the popiſh or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Miniſters, which is not onely ſtraunge from the word of God and the vſe of all well reformed churches in the world, but is alſo drawen out of the Popes pontificall, wherein he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf to be Antichriſt most lively; that is to have confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with Antichriſt and his Officers as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But ſuch is the execution of the Miniſterie of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to have conformity with Antichrist and his Officers as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Propoſition they will not gaineſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Aſſumption they have graunted and publiſhed,</hi> 
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>vidz</abbr>
                     <expan>vide licet</expan>
                  </choice>, That they have an Antichristian Hierarchie and popiſh or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Ministers, straunge from the word of God and the vſe of all well reformed Churches in the world; <hi>And,</hi> that their Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticfiall whereby they conſecrate Biſhops and make Miniſters and Deacons, is nothing els but a thing word for word drawen out of the Popes pontificall, wherein he ſheweth himſelf to be Antichriſt most lively. Admon. to Parliam. treatiſe <hi>2.</hi> ſection <hi>14.</hi> and 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:4135:51"/>
               <head>The third Argument, taken out of the ſame book of Mr Bradſh. Twelve Arguments, and out of the London Miniſters Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, and Lincolnſhire Miniſters Abridgement <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IF ſuch be the eſtate of the Ministery of the Church-aſſemblies of England, as they are bound in their Ministration vnto ſuch things, as the vſing of them in Church Service in manner and forme preſcribed, is a Wil-worſhip; a giving of ſpeciall Honour to Antichriſt and his members; a performing of Honour more then civill (even a Religious) onely to an humane Power and Authority; a warranting of the like vſe of Iewiſh, Turkiſh, Paganiſh, or Popiſh obſervations; a doing of ſchiſmaticall Actions; an having of ſpirituall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Idolatrous Papiſts in the mysteries of their Idolatrie and Superſtition; a mingling of Profane things with Divine; an vſing of vnlawfull things in Divine worſhip; an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring of Sacraments that are not of divine institution; a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne acknowledging of ſpirituall Homage, to the ſpirituall vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authority of Lord Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops; an vſing of humane Traditions and Rites enioyned to be performed in Gods worſhip, as neceſſarie to ſalvation; an apparant meanes of the Damnation of the ſowles of infinite numbers of men, confirming them in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry; a diſgracing of the holy Scripture; a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning of the Sacraments; an approving of Popiſh errours, and manifest vntruths; an obſerving of a Leiturgie which in the whole matter and forme thereof, is too like vnto the Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book, and hath in it ſundry things contrary to the word of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If ſuch (I ſay) be the estate of the Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England, then is it not lawfull to communicate with them therein.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But ſuch is the eſtate of the Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</hi> Ergo,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>It is not lawfull to communicate with them therein.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:4135:52"/>The conſequence of the Propoſition is proved by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry reaſons alledged<note n="*" place="margin">Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the book delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, by the Lincolneſhire Ministers. p. <hi>17.</hi> &amp;c.</note> by the Lincolneſhire Miniſters, though vrged by them but againſt the vſe of their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: which we will now apply vnto the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with their Miniſterie and miniſtration aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the ſecond commandement, which forbids all provocations vnto ſpiritual fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the ſeventh doth vnto that which is carnall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the commandement and direction God hath given vs in his word, † to ſeparate our ſelves from Idolaters <hi>and Antichristians,</hi> and to be as vnlike vnto them as may be, ſpecially in their religious obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ‖ to aboliſh not onely all Idols but all the inſtruments of Idolatrie, and that ſo as we may beſt ſhew our ‡ vtmoſt deteſtation to them and *root out the verie memory of them, &amp;c. †<hi>Levit. 18.3.4 and 19.19.27, 28. Exod. 23.24. Deut. 14.1. and 12.4, 30, 32, 2 Cor. 6.14-18. Apoca. 18.4.</hi> ‖ <hi>Gen. 35.2, 4. Num. 33.52. Deut. 12.2.3.</hi> 2 <hi>King. 23.4, 5. Eſa. 27.9. and 30.22.23. Zeph. 1.4. Apoca. 2, 14.20.</hi> ‡ <hi>Deut. 7.25.26. and 9.21.</hi> 1 <hi>Chron. 14.12. 2 King. 18.4. and 23.6.8. Eſa. 30.22. Iude,</hi> 23. * <hi>Exod. 23.13. Deut. 12.3. Ioſh. 23.7. Zach. 13.</hi>2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the equity &amp; reaſons of theſe commandements which we find ſet down in holy Scripture. <hi>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>vidz</abbr>
                        <expan>vide licet</expan>
                     </choice>, 1.</hi> The deteſtation which the Lord our God (being a jelous God) beareth vnto Idolatry and all the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and tokens thereof, as vnto ſpirituall whoredome. <hi>Exod. 20.5.6. Deut. 7.25.26. 2.</hi> That we cannot be ſaid ſincerely to have repented of the <hi>Antichriſtianiſme</hi> Idolatrie or ſuperſtition whereby we or our forefathers have provoked the Lord, vnles we be aſhamed of and caſt away with deteſtation all the inſtruments and monuments of it. <hi>2 Chron. 33.15. Eſa. 1.28.29. and</hi> 2.<hi>6.8.9.20. and 30.9.10.11.</hi>22. <hi>2 Cor. 7.11.</hi> 3. That we ſhalbe in danger to be corrupted in Religion and doctrine, and to be brought to ruine and deſtruction, if we conforme our ſelves to Idolaters <hi>&amp; Antichriſtians</hi> in their Miniſterie, miniſtration, ceremonies, &amp; reteyne or partake with the monuments of their ſuperſtition, yea if we ſhew not al deteſtation vnto them. <hi>Exod. 34.12.15. Deut. 7.4.25.26. Iudg. 2.13. Gal.</hi> 2.<hi>5. Rev. 18.4. 4.</hi> That our keeping of communion with the Miniſters in ſuch Miniſtration, will be a ſpeciall meane to harden them in that vngodlynes. <hi>Ezech. 16.54. 1 Cor. 8.10.</hi> 5. That ſeing the Prelates are reveiled to be great Antichriſts, and their Miniſterie and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be great troublers of the Church at this day, it cannot but be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinfull and hurtfull to reteyne or communicate with them. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.<hi>3.4.8.9.10.</hi>11.<hi>12. Apoc. 17. and 18. chap. Lev. 18.3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. By the judgment of the godly learned of all Churches &amp; ages, who
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:4135:52"/>
have conſtantly taught and given teſtimony to this truth, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are bound to forſake and caſt of the Miniſtration ceremonies &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious cuſtomes of Pagans Iewes <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> Idolaters &amp; Hereticks, and carefully to ſhun all conformity with them therein.</p>
               <p>And hitherto of ſuch reaſons as are alledged by the Lincolneſhire Miniſters, as is aforeſaid. Now for further confirmation of the Propoſition, I will alſo annex theſe following; being of like nature with the former.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The conſideration of the many ſinnes, and thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo great and grievous, which enſue vpon ſuch practiſe: as may appeare by the particulars noted here in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, &amp; proſecuted in their Books.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the ſecond commandement forbiddeth not onely <hi>the making,</hi> but alſo <hi>the bowing downe</hi> to any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions &amp; conſtitutions of men in the worſhip of God: And this prohibition of <hi>bowing downe,</hi> includeth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe that vſe them, but ſuch alſo as communicate with them therein. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Lord requireth of vs to ſhew all vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deteſtation and forſaking of them, both by word &amp; deed, even caſting them away as menſtruous cloths, and ſaying vnto them, Get you hence. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.22.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe the impoſition &amp; obſervation of the things aforeſayd, is not onely vpon the Miniſters, but vpon the people alſo, &amp; that both in their own perſons and in their children. And why ſhould not the people aſwel as the Miniſters ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made them free, and not be intangled agayne with the yoke of bondage? <hi>Gal. 5.</hi>1.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe the Lord hath not required this at our hands, that we ſhould ſerve him by ſuch a Miniſterie and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And finally, becauſe the Lord hath ſtraitly enjoyned vs to forſake all humane deviſes in his worſhip, and not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:4135:53"/>
at all to partake with any of the ſinnes of Babylon. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>chap. Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>and</hi> 22.18.19. Of which ſort, both they and we have proved that theſe are: as may be ſeen in their books and ours written hereabout. And thus much of the Propoſition.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption is proved by Mr Bradſh. in his <hi>Twelve Arguments;</hi> by the London Miniſters in their <hi>Exceptions;</hi> and by the Lincolneſhire Miniſters in their <hi>Abridgement of the Book delivered to his Maieſty: pag.</hi> 2-70. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>the Canons of Anno</hi> 1603. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Arguments &amp; other Treatiſes of the Miniſters, ſhew the nature and vſe of the things enioyned to be of ſuch conſequence. The Canons of the Convocation and other Lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of their Church, ſhew that the Miniſters are bound to ſuch a Miniſtration: And that vpon payne of ſuſpenſion, deprivation, degradation, excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Wherevpon ſome of them have written, that<note n="*" place="margin">Removal of Imput. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von &amp; Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall Minist. p. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>not Paul himſelf, if he were living, ſhould be permitted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his function, if he would not conforme:</hi> And,<note n="‡" place="margin">Mr Bradſh. Argum. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the whole Solemne Worſhip and Ministerie of Ieſus must ſtoupe and yeeld to theſe; And theſe must not stoupe or yeeld to them.</hi> Which howſoever they apply moſt vnto their Ceremonies, yet the grounds of their Arguments imply it alſo vpon their Miniſtery, and vpon the partakers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: as may appeare by that which hath ben ſayd before; &amp; which hereafter followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:4135:53"/>
               <head>The fourth Argument, taken out of the Admonitions to the Parliament, written by the Preachers ſeeking reformation,</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IF the Offices of the Archbiſhops, Archdeacons, Lordbiſhops, Suffraganes, Parſons, Vicars, Pariſh priests, Stipendaries, and the reſt of that ſort in the Church of England, be Antichristian &amp; contrarie to the Scriptures: then the people of God may not heare or otherwiſe partake with their Ministerie in the worſhip of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Offices of the Archbiſhops, Archdeacons, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Suffraganes, Parſons, Vicars, Pariſh priests, Stipendaries, and the reſt of that ſort in the Church of England, are Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and contrarie to the Scriptures.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Therefore the people of God may not heare or otherwiſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with their Miniſtery in the worſhip of God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Propoſition needs no proof. For what communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath light with darknes? And what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? 2</hi> Cor. <hi>6.14-17.</hi> Rev. <hi>14.9-12.</hi> and <hi>18.4.</hi> and <hi>22.18.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Aſſumption is their owne ſaying, and their plea for reformation many yeares ſince. <hi>Admonition to the Parliam. treatiſe,</hi> 1. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>ſection,</hi> 14.18.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:4135:54"/>
               <head>The fift Argument, taken out of the Offer of Conference or diſputation, tendered by ſome of the ſilenced &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived Miniſters, to the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, &amp;c.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IF theſe Propoſitions be true,</hi> 1. <hi>That all matters meerly Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, which are lawfully impoſed vpon any Church, are ſuch as may be concluded neceſſarily from the written word of God:</hi> 2. <hi>That all humane Ordinances vſed onely or ſpecially in Gods worſhip, wherevnto they are not neceſſarie of themſelves, are ſimply vnlawfull:</hi> 3. <hi>That every true viſible Church of Chriſt is ſuch a ſpirituall Body politick, as is ſpecially inſtituted by Christ or his Apoſtles in the New Testament:</hi> 4. <hi>That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true viſible Church of Chriſt or ordinary Aſſembly of the faithfull, hath by Chriſts ordinance power in it ſelf, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnder Christ, to elect and ordeyne, deprive and depoſe their Miniſters, &amp; to execute all other Eccleſiasticall Cenſures:</hi> 5. <hi>That the Paſtor of a particular Congregation is the higheſt ordinary ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Officer in any true constituted viſible Church of Chriſt:</hi> 6. <hi>That it is the Office of every true Pastor to teach and to governe ſpiritually onely one Church or Congregation im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately vnder Christ:</hi> 7. <hi>That the Office &amp; Calling of Provinciall and Dioceſan Prelates is contrary to the word of God: If (I ſay) theſe Propoſitions be true, then it is not lawfull to hear or have any ſpirituall communion with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Propoſitions aforeſaid are true.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore it is not lawful to heare or have any ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the preſent Ministerie of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Major is of neceſſary conſequence, and not to be denyed: 1. Becauſe their Eccleſiaſticall matters Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:4135:54"/>
Offices &amp; Miniſtration, called into queſtion, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be concluded from the written word of God; but are Humane Ordinances, never inſtituted by Chriſt or his Apoſtles: And therefore are vnlawfull to be received or bowed vnto in Gods worſhip. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4.5. <hi>and</hi> 23.13.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.28-32. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14-17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. <hi>and</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>Iude, ver. 3. &amp;</hi> 23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe by the conſequence of theſe Propoſitions, they have not in their eſtate eyther true Churches or true Miniſters. And with falſe Churches and falſe Miniſters, we may not have any ſpirituall communion. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Amos. 4.4.</hi>5. <hi>Ioh. 10.5. Reve.</hi> 14.9-12. <hi>and</hi> 18.<hi>4.5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Neyther can it be but that ſuch practiſe muſt needs imply in them which do it, that eyther they hold the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions aforeſayd to be falſe (which they averr to be true) or at leaſt that they walk corruptly &amp; halt between two opinions. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21.</p>
               <p>The Minor is profeſſed and publiſhed by themſelves, and offered to be mainteyned againſt the Archbiſhops and Biſhops and all their adherents, by the late ſilenced and deprived Miniſters in England. <hi>Offer of Conference, pag.</hi> 1.2.</p>
               <p>Where alſo note, how themſelves hold it lawfull, vpon the Prelates proceedings, that<note n="*" place="margin">Offer of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, pag. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>both the Miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Church-aſſemblies of England may leave their ordinarie standing in thoſe Churches.</hi> Which if it prove not a lawfull ſeparation like ours, it wilbe found to be a very ſchiſme among themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:4135:55"/>
               <head>The ſixt Argument, taken out of divers Treatiſes written in behalf of the Miniſters of Devonſhire, Cornwall, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire &amp;c. alſo out of the Admonitions to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; out of Mr Cartwrights, Mr Vdals, Mr Iacobs, &amp; other of their books, written of like argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF theſe Aſſertions be true,</hi> 1. <hi>That that Church-calling for which the Scripture giveth no expreſſe warrant, is meerly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped &amp; vtterly vnlawfull:</hi> 2. <hi>That as it is not lawful to bring in any ſtraunge doctrine, ſo is it not lawfull to teach the true doctrine, vnder the name of any other function then is inſtituted by God;</hi> And, <hi>that God hath not onely ordeyned that the word ſhould be preached, but hath ordeyned alſo in what order and by whom it ſhould be preached:</hi> 3. <hi>That the Word of God contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Writings of the Prophets and Apostles, is of abſolute perfection, given by Chriſt the head of the Church, to be vnto the ſame, the ſole Canon and rule of all matters of Religion, and the worſhip and ſervice of God whatſoever: And that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever done in the ſame ſervice and worſhip cannot be iustifyed by the ſaid word, is vnlawfull:</hi> 4. <hi>That a true viſible Church is a company of men, ordinarily ioyning together in the true worſhip of God: And, that all ſuch Churches and Congregations, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating after that maner together, in divine worſhip, are in all eccleſiaſticall matters equall, and of the ſame power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and that by the word and will of God they ought to have the ſame ſpiritual priviledges, prerogatives, officers, administrations, orders, and Formes of divine worſhip:</hi> 5. <hi>That every esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church or Congregation ought to have thoſe ſpirituall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Miniſters which are enioyned by Chriſt in the new Teſtament, and no other:</hi> 6. <hi>That the ground of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is the Kingly function of Christ, who is the Head of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:4135:55"/>
Church, and whom it properly concernes to make lawes by which to governe the Church.</hi> 7. <hi>That the Scripture hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an exact platforme of Pollicie for the Houſe of God which is the Church:</hi> And, <hi>The word of God deſcribeth perfitly vnto vs, that form of governing the Church w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is lawful; &amp; the officers that are to execute the ſame; from the which no Chriſtian Church ought to ſwarve.</hi> 8. <hi>That the forme of Church-governement in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland is an Humane ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; yea &amp; the very ſame, by which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist roſe vnto his intollerable Tyranny in Gods Church.</hi> 9. <hi>That it robbeth the Church of lawfull Paſtors, Elders, and Deacons.</hi> 10. <hi>That Dioceſan Biſhops have not any place nor part at all in any true and proper viſible Church of Christ.</hi> 11. <hi>That it is the naturall and immutable office of a Pastor both to Teach and to Governe (with the aſsiſtance of other Elders) his owne flock.</hi> 12. <hi>That the right &amp; true Diſcipline Eccleſiasticall in each proper Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, is one mayne part of the ordinarie meanes of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appointed by God for every ſoule: and that this in the Church of England is vtterly wanting.</hi> 13. <hi>That Dioceſan Biſhops, &amp;c. do (by neceſſarie conſequence) deny Chriſt the Saviour to be our intire and perfect Prophet and ſpirituall King (by taking away from him ſome proper parts of his Propheticall and Kingly Offices), impugne the Foundation of ſaving faith, and are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to Gods word.</hi> 14. <hi>That Chriſt is the onely teacher of his Church, and appointer of all meanes whereby we ſhould be taught and admoniſhed of any holy dutie, &amp; whatſoever he hath thought good to teach his Church, and the meanes whereby, he hath perfitly ſet downe in the holy Scriptures, ſo that to acknowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other meanes of teaching and admoniſhing vs of our duty, then ſuch as he hath appointed, is to receive another teacher into the the Church beſides him, and to confeſſe ſome imperfection in thoſe meanes he hath ordeyned to teach vs by: If theſe Aſſertions (I ſay) be true, then is it vnlawfull to have communion with the preſent Ministery of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:4135:56"/>
                  <hi>But the foreſaid Aſſertions are true:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore it is vnlawfull to have communion with the preſent Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Propoſition agreeth with that of the former Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and addeth weight vnto it. For, beſides that which there is ſayd, it cannot ſtand with the Homage due vnto Chriſt the King and Head of the Church; with the ſound acknowledgement of the ſufficiency of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; word of God; with the carefull vſing of the means of ſalvation appointed by God for every ſoule; with the faithfull renouncing of all humane ordinances in Gods worſhip, and vtter deteſtation of Antichriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with the Miniſterie of the Church-aſſemblies of England: ſeing they are not lawfull Paſtors or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, having the naturall and immutable Offices appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt, nor performing the worſhip of God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Canon of his word; but ſtand in ſubiection to Provinciall and Dioceſan Biſhops, receiving their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery from them, and executing it vnder them, who are contrary to Gods word, and againſt the Prophecy &amp; Kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So as to heare and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with their Miniſtery, were to worſhip God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an vnlawfull maner, and to acknowledge other offices and meanes of teaching and governing the Church, then ſuch as Chriſt hath appointed: and conſequently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an other Teacher &amp; King into the Church beſides him, and to confeſſe ſome imperfection in thoſe offices and meanes which he hath ordeyned to teach &amp; governe vs by. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Aſſumption is their owne, acknowledged &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by themſelves in divers of their books: Namely,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:4135:56"/>
                  <hi>The Removall of certaine Imputations layd vpon the Ministers of Devon: and Cornwall, pag.</hi> 22. 39. <hi>T. C. reply,</hi> 1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 83. <hi>Engliſh Puritaniſme, p.</hi> 1. 5. 6. 12. 13. 24. <hi>The Demonſtrat. of Diſcipl. pag</hi> 1. <hi>Admonit. to the Parliam. treatiſe,</hi> 1. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. 37. <hi>Mr Iacobs Reaſons proving ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of reforming the Churches in England, pag.</hi> 33. 35. 51. 52. 53. <hi>The Abridgement of the Book delivered to his Maieſty by the Lincolnſhire Miniſt: pag.</hi> 31. 32. 77. 78. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let it here be obſerved, that although the caſe be thus cleare, by their owne writings, againſt their Church and Miniſtery: yet<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. Bradſh. Argum. <hi>12.</hi> London Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Protest. Mr Iacobs, Mr Hilderſ. Mr Stones, &amp; others wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. &amp;c.</note> they ceaſe not to impute <hi>ſchiſme</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs for ſeparating from them in ſuch eſtate; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that <hi>the mayne cauſe of our ſeparation, is becauſe of their Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies;</hi> they hold and plead that <hi>the Churches of England, as they be establiſhed by publik Authority, are true viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt;</hi> and that <hi>their Ministers, are faithfull Pastors, and true Ministers of Christ,</hi> &amp;c. Accuſations, pretences, opinions and pleas, that ſort very ill with their Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Aſſertions: and are ſo much the more ſtraunge in them, as they have, beſides all the former Poſitions &amp; many other the like, affirmed expreſſely, that <hi>they lack both a right Ministerie of God, &amp; a right governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his Church according to the Scriptures;</hi> that <hi>they have an Antichristian hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie; &amp;</hi> a Leiturgy <hi>culled &amp; picked out of the Popiſh dunghil the Maſſebook full of all abominations;</hi> and that <hi>the controverſie betwixt the Prelates &amp; them, is not for a cap a tippet or a ſurplus, but for greater matters concerning a true Miniſterie and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church according to the word. Which being once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, the other melt away of themſelves. Admon. to the Parliam. treatiſe,</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Thus have they written and iudged themſelves here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. Now if their Church and Miniſtery were altered,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:4135:57"/>
it would be knowen. But ſeing it is not, how is it that they keep not more to the greater matters in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; but inſiſt ſo much vpon the leſſer, which would <hi>melt away of themſelves, if the other were once establiſhed?</hi> And why blame they vs, for ſeparating from their falſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, vnlawfull worſhip, and Babyloniſh conſtitution of their Church? Or why conſider they not, that the extent of their Propoſitions and Aſſertions reacheth, not onely to their Ceremonies, but alſo to their Miniſtery, Leiturgie, and Church it ſelf?</p>
               <p>Now therefore if they can make to accord together, their judgement with their practiſe, their writings with their walking: it is more then tyme &amp; needfull that they did it, &amp; that they did it ſoundly from the word of God. For as yet what do they els, but with one mouth both bleſſe and curſe; and with the one hand build vp that which with the other they deſtroy, and ſo make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves treſpaſſers? <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:4135:57"/>
               <head>The ſeventh Argument, taken out of Mr Bradſh. book aforeſaid: <choice>
                     <abbr>vidz,</abbr>
                     <expan>vide licet</expan>
                  </choice> out of the tenth Argument of that Treatiſe.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IT is a ſinne against Chriſt the ſole Head of the Church, to have ſpirituall communion with thoſe Ministers, which in the administration of Divine things, do eyther by word or deed, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely profeſſe &amp; yeeld a ſpirituall Homage, to an vſurped ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall authority in the Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Miniſters of the Church-aſſemblies of England, do even in the administration of Divine things, by ſolemne deed, profeſſe and yeeld a ſpirituall Homage, to the ſpirituall authority of Lord Archbiſhops and Biſhops, which is vſurped.</hi> Ergo,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>It is a ſinne againſt Chriſt the ſole head of the Church to have ſpirituall communion with the Miniſters of the Church aſſemblies of England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Propoſition may not be gaineſaid: For all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power vſurped over the Churches of God, is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian authority, and to communicate with thoſe Miniſters which profeſſe ſpirituall homage therevnto, is to communicate with ſuch as profeſſe ſpiritual homage vnto Antichriſt, which muſt needs be a ſin againſt Chriſt the ſole head of the Church.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption hath two parts:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Ministers of the Church of England do even in the adminiſtration of Divine things, by ſolemne deed, profeſſe and yeeld a ſpirituall Homage to the ſpirituall authoritie of Archbiſhops and Lord Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is moſt evident, becauſe they preach the word and adminiſter the Sacraments by vertue of their calling received from the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, who give them authority herevnto at their ordination,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:4135:58"/>
ſaying to every one of them,<note n="*" place="margin">Book of orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Priests fol. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Take thou authority to preach the word of God, and to Minister the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Congregation, where thou ſhalt be ſo appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> Which things themſelves cannot deny to be meer Eccleſiaſticall, Religious and ſpirituall Actions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned among them to be done by offices &amp; callings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Prelates Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: So as the doing of them by vertue thereof, muſt needs be a ſolemne declaration of ſpirituall homage yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſame authority.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond part of the Aſſumption is: <hi>That the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their Lord Archbiſhops and Biſhops is an vſurped au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> The confirmation whereof, Mr Bradſh. ſetteth downe in theſe words following:</p>
               <p>This is ſufficiently proved of late by <hi>Mr Iacob,</hi> in his 1. Aſſertion by many reaſons. Onely becauſe the weight of the Argument leaneth vpon it, I will vſe one Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thoſe Officers &amp; Rulers in the Church that make claime to be of Divine inſtitution, chalenge to themſelves Apostolicall authority and iuriſdiction as the onely Succeſſours of the Apoſtles; to ſit onely in Moſes chaire; To have ſole power of the Keyes; To cut from the viſible Church, and receive againe: To have power of creating &amp; diſplacing all other eccleſiaſticall officers; To be the Vniverſall Pastors of whole Dukedomes and Kingdomes, vnder whom all other Pastors are as Curates, &amp;c. And yet for all this, are ſuch as ſtand and are ſupported onely by humane Traditions &amp; Ceremonies, ſuch as a civill Magiſtrate may without ſinne, put out of the Church, and ſuch as the true Churches of God may renounce (and yet continue the true Church) as Antichristian Vſurpers &amp; ſpirituall Tyrants: (I ſay) all ſuch Officers and Rulers exerciſe an vſurped authoritie in the Church:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:4135:58"/>
                  <hi>But our Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops are ſuch Rulers and Officers as are aforeſaid.</hi> Ergo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They execute an Vſurped power over the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Propoſition may eaſily be iuſtified. For if inferiour officers, <choice>
                     <abbr>vidz,</abbr>
                     <expan>vide licet</expan>
                  </choice> Paſtors of particular Congregations, have had &amp; may have firme continuance in the Church, without theſe humane deviſes and inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; If the Magiſtrate cannot without ſinn put them out of the Church; And if thoſe can be no true Churches that renounce to have particular Paſtours and Miniſters over them, it muſt much more hold in ſuch Church-officers and Rulers as theſe are, if their authority be lawfull &amp; good: For whileſt the Apoſtles lived, they needed not any humane Traditions and deviſes to ſupport their authority: The Magiſtrates that ſought to put them downe ſinned with a high hand: And that was no Church, that renounced and diſclaimed their Office, Authoritie and Iuriſdiction.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption is as eaſily juſtified. For 1. they make claime &amp; Title to all thoſe Prerogatives before rehearſed in the firſt part of the Propoſition, and vnto more then that, as ſhalbe proved if it be denied.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is an Embleme of their owne <hi>NO CEREMONIE, NO BISHOP.</hi> Ergo, <hi>No humane Tradition and Invention, no Biſhop, Ergo,</hi> The office of a Biſhop is ſupported by them eyther onely or ſpecially.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction is derived from the King, els it is a flat deniall of his Supremacie. Alſo themſelves graunt in their laſt Tables of Diſcipline, That the King hath power to increaſe or diminiſh the Circuit of a Biſhoprick: That he may make two or more Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks of one, &amp; one Biſhoprick to be two or more: Yea what ſhould hinder but that he may divide the Biſhoprick of London into 800. For where God hath not defined the number of Pariſhes that a Biſhop is to reign over, it muſt needs be a thing indifferent: In which by their owne Doctrines the King hath authority without ſinne, to diſpoſe. If therefore the King may as well (notwithſtanding any thing in the Law of God) give the Keyes of the Church to everie particular Paſtour of a Congregation, over his owne Congregation, as to a Biſhop over a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe, which taketh away the very Eſſence of an Engliſh Biſhop, He may without ſinne take away the very Office of the Biſhop, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in having juriſdiction over many Congregations. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. There is no true &amp; ſober Chriſtians but will ſay that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Scotland; Fraunce,</hi> the low Countries, and other places (that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſuch Archbiſhops and Biſhops (as ours are) as Antichriſtian &amp; vſurping Prelates) are true Churches of God: Which they could not be, if the authoritie and prerogatives they claime to themſelves, were
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:4135:59"/>
of Chriſt, and not vſurped. For if it were the ordinance of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that in every Kingdome, that receiveth the Goſpel, there ſhould be one Archbiſhop over the whole Kingdome: One Biſhop over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred Paſtors in a Kingdome, and all they inveſted with that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and juriſdiction Apoſtolicall which they claime <hi>iure Divino,</hi> to be due vnto them, and to reſide in them, by the ordinance of Chriſt, certainely that Church that ſhould renounce and diſclaime ſuch an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ordeyned in the Church, cannot be a true Church but a Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Sathan. For they that ſhould renounce and deny ſuch, muſt needs therein renounce and deny Chriſt himſelf. Thus the Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is cleared.</p>
               <p>And thus the cauſe is yeelded, by themſelves: who in their owne writings ſpeak and reaſon in ſuch ſort, as hath ben ſhewed. Which I thought good thus to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to their preſent eſtate, &amp; further manifeſtation of the truth. And thus much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theſe Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Which now I leave to the conſideration of all that are of judgement and conſcience: exhorting them as they love the truth and their owne good,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Theſ. 5.21. Pſal. 119.59</note> to try all things by the word of God, to conſider their wayes, and to turn their feet into his teſtimonies.</p>
               <p>And I pray the Lord God of all glorie and goodnes, to diſcover and conſume the apoſtaſie of Antichriſt dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more; to make the light and power of the Goſpell of Chriſt ſhine forth and prevaile againſt all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and hinderances; &amp; to give his people of all eſtates and nations to walk in the light and comfort thereof, to the praiſe of his Name, and eternall life, by Ieſus Chriſt: who is God overall bleſſed for ever. Amen.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ier. 50.29.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Call together<note n="*" place="margin">the mighty</note> many againſt Babel, all that bend the bow, beſiege her round about, let there be no eſcaping for her: recompenſe her according to her work, according to all that ſhe hath done, do vnto her: for ſhe hath ben proude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, againſt the holy one of Iſrael.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4135:59"/>
            <head>A Table of ſome principall things conteyned in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THat it is not lawfull to heare or have any ſpirituall communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with other Ministerie then that which Christ hath given vnto his Church. pag. <hi>1. 17. 51. 63. 70. 78. 87. 93.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>That the Ministery given by Chriſt, is of Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangelists, Paſtors and Teachers, ſpoken of <hi>Epheſ. 4.</hi> p. <hi>2. 4. 5. 7. 22.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>That the Miniſters of the Church of England are none of theſe. p. <hi>3.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Of the obiection made about hearing the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees. p. <hi>14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Miniſtery of the Church of Engl. is the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie. p. <hi>18.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Of the Prelates being ſpirituall Lords, Dioceſan and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Biſhops, Antichriſtian vſurpers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi> &amp;c. and p. <hi>70. 71. 101. 102. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the examples of Timothee and Titus alledged for them. p. <hi>22.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Two Queſtions, about the ordinance of Chriſt, and the apoſtaſie of Antichrist, touching the Ministery and governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church. p. <hi>26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the Ministers of the Church of England are made Deacons, Priests, Biſhops and Archbiſhops: And wherevnto they ſubſcribe. p. <hi>30.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>That the Ministery of that Church obeyeth not Christ in his ordinance as their Prophet Priest and King. p. <hi>39. 105.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it is ſet againſt and exalted above the holy things
<pb facs="tcp:4135:60"/>
and constitutions of Chriſt. p. <hi>41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it apperteyneth not properly to any eſtate, civill or eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, but onely to the body and religion of Antichriſt. p. <hi>42. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the King may and ought to ſuppreſſe it throughout his Dominions. p. <hi>44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Lord will aboliſh it, by the light and power of his Goſpell, with the ſpirit of his mouth and brightnes of his coming. p. <hi>46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Miniſters with the people in that eſtate worſhip the Beasts image, and receive his mark in the forehead or hand. p. <hi>51.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>That they derive not their power and functions of Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie from Christ the head of the Church. p. <hi>63.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>That though they be of good gifts and teach many true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, yet it is no warrant to communicate with their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. p. <hi>66. 75. 92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That they work vpon the conſciences of men by vertue of a falſe ſpirituall calling. p. <hi>70. 109. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Apostles not ceaſing to preach in the Name of Ieſus, at the commandement of the Rulers of Iſrael. p. <hi>73. 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Miniſterie of the Church of Engl. is a ſtraunge Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery. p. <hi>78.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Of the conſpiracy of Corah Dathan Abiram &amp;c. p. <hi>79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it is vnlawfull to preſent our bodies at falſe worſhip. p. <hi>81.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Of Naamans example alledged for that purpoſe. p. <hi>82.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Ministerie of the Church of England is not from heaven, but of men. p. <hi>87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it giveth honour to Antichriſt, and is derogatory to the reformed Churches. p. <hi>95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Divers testimonies of their owne, and of the Martyrs &amp; others, against their Miniſterie and Church estate. p. <hi>6. 13. 15. 21. 30. 33. 36. 41. 44. 59. 65. 73. 76. 79. 88. 93.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4135:60"/>Alſo the grounds of Mr Bradſh. Arguments, and of the London, Lincolnſhire, Devonſhire, and other ſilenced Ministers, their Exceptions, Abridgement, Anſwers, and Offers, applyed againſt them. p. <hi>93.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Pag. 63. lin. 6. &amp; 7. read thus: <hi>of Engl. is ſuch as deriveth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 78. lin. 22. <hi>Num.</hi> 15.39.</p>
            <p>Pag. 85. lin. 8. <hi>will from the hote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 94. line 29. (annex this in ſuch of the books where it is wanting) <hi>and God muſt have no ſolemne Worſhip in England, except it be in communion with the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 95. lin. 19. put in the margent, <hi>Mr Bradſh. Argum.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Pag. 110. lin. 10. annex this, <hi>And their owne reaſons alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt the vſe of the Ceremonies do alſo prove it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
